<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nissena, an excellent new romance: / written originally in Italian by Francesco Carmeni; and now Englished by an honorable anti-socordist.</title>
            <author>Carmeni, Francesco.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1234_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210434</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869234</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121609</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121609)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 253:E1234[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nissena, an excellent new romance: / written originally in Italian by Francesco Carmeni; and now Englished by an honorable anti-socordist.</title>
                  <author>Carmeni, Francesco.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his Shop at the sign of the Princes-Arms in St Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653. [i.e. 1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1st Decemb 1652."; the 3 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121609:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NISSENA, AN EXCELLENT NEW ROMANCE: WRITTEN Originally in ITALIAN BY <hi>FRANCESCO CARMENI;</hi> AND Now Engliſhed by an Honorable ANTI-SOCORDIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the ſign of the Princes Arms in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> PAULS Church-yard, 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:121609:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121609:2"/>
            <head>NISSENA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HOAS</hi> King of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat aged, was much afflicted for that he wanted one to ſucceed him in his Kingdome, having utterly loſt all hopes thereof by the death of his wife <hi>Almira,</hi> daughter to the late King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who died being with child. He thought it unbecoming Kingly Majeſty to marry a Subject, though he wanted not good ſtore of Noble bloud, and cry'd up beauty. And to ally himſelfe with his neighbouring Princes, ſuited not with his politick ends; wherefore moved thereunto by his naturall inclination, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to take unto him ſuch a wife, as might acknowledge her being made part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Regall Throne onely to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of her beauty. <hi>Rhodes,</hi> a neighbouring Iſland, though but of a ſmall circuit, was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121609:3"/>in thoſe dayes ſo famous for handſome wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and did ſo much abound therein, as young Travellers flockt thither from farre diſtant Provinces, onely to feed their gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and curious eyes, with beholding thoſe countenances which multiplied <hi>Venus'es</hi> on earth, and out-did the ſtarres in Heaven. <hi>Thoas</hi> therefore, putting on a ſtrange reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, determined to ſend thither three of the ancienteſt and wiſeſt Gentlemen of his Court, with free liberty to bring her unto him whom of all the Virgins of that Iſland they ſhould judge to be the faireſt, that he might make her a Companion both of his Bed and Kingdome, to the end that the one might be bleſſed with iſſue, the other with ſucceſſors. He recommended three qualities to be by them obſerved in her whom they were to chuſe to be his Queen. That ſhe ſhould be of Noble Birth, Of an excellent Temper, And of a befitting Age. And for a fourth, he gave them in charge, that ſhe ſhould be rarely handſome, to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the World, that he did not marry meerly out of a deſire to ſatisfie his luſt. The Ambaſſadors departed with two of the moſt glorious and beſt rig'd Gallies which were ever made in the Kings Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, attended on with a number of Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Souldiers, and Servants, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121609:3"/>to the decencie and greatneſs of him that ſent them. Having had a very proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous paſſage, they caſt Anchor not far from the Haven, which on the Eaſt is ſhut in by two ſtrong necks of land, thruſt out by the Iſland to reſt her ſelf upon. The uſuall friendly Salute being given by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſhot, they ſent <hi>Albericus,</hi> one of the Gentlemen, upon the Peere, with the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Enſignes, who made <hi>Fermondo</hi> the then Prince underſtand, That three Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors from <hi>Cyprus</hi> deſired his good leave to come on ſhore, and to have audience: He being full of Civility, and a friend to that Crown, ſent forthwith many of his Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen unto the Haven, who went forth in three ſtately veſſels, to meet and reverently to receive the Ambaſſadors. When they were come on land, and being put into rich Coaches, they were waited upon to the Palace by many of the chiefeſt of the <hi>Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Nobility. They were met at the ſtairs head by <hi>Fermondo's</hi> ſelfe; and after multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied Embraces and Welcomes, they were brought into the Kings lodging: they were well pleaſed to ſee themſelves treated with greater reſpect and ſtate then they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or could have imagined. Being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what weary, by reaſon of thoſe unavoidable troubles which are ſuffered at Sea, were bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121609:4"/>in ſleep when the Sun was well advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from the eaſt; and when they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened by the gladſome ſound of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and the beating of Drums, which in warlike wiſe congratulated the arrivall of ſuch conſpicuous perſonages. As ſoon as they were dreſt they were invited to Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by the Prince, who very affably mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them, ſaid, What is it that is deſired by the Ambaſſadors of King <hi>Thoas,</hi> whom I ſo love and reverence, as I have taken but little reſt all the laſt night, out of my deſire ſpeediy to execute the commands of ſo worthy a King? With all due reverence, and as much eloquence as they were Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of, they delivered their Ambaſſie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring that his Highneſſe would be pleaſed that out of all the faireſt and beſt born Maids of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> one may be choſen to make happy by her Marriage and Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Bed &amp; Bloud Royal of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> The Prince gave way unto their deſires, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a pleaſing countenance, How for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate are you the Virgins of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> for whom your propitious Stars and <hi>Thoas</hi> his goodneſſe hath prepared ſo conſiderable fortunes? Return my acknowledgements unto your King, who vouchſafes to chuſe a Companion out of my Subjects, who though I command over them, am yet his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121609:4"/>humble ſervant. Thankfull Civilities were paid on all ſides, and in execution of the requeſt, publick proclamation was made, That all the faireſt and beſt born Virgins of <hi>Rhodes</hi> ſhould withing a certain prefixt time come to Court, where ſhe who ſhould be judged to be the handſomeſt, ſhould be crowned Queen of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> This was ſoon noyſed over the whole Iſland, to the great wonder of every one; and to the particular, alteration of the hearts, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the young Maids, but of their Lovers. There was no ſo conceal'd corner in the breaſts of all thoſe Maids, which was not fild with ambition &amp; womaniſh vainglory; &amp; the belief which all Lovers have, that the object of their affection is the onely true I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doll of beauty, did much torment the young men, every one of them fearing to loſe her whom they thought to be as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a Crown as ſhe appear'd to them to be the Queen of Beauty. Some of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins more paſſionatly in love then the reſt, would have refuſed to have appeared at the time and place appointed, though a Scepter depended thereupon, leſt they might loſe their Sweet-hearts, had not their Parents ambitious hopes forced them to goe. The houre and place were appointed, which was to be the fatall moment and Capitoll to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121609:5"/>Triumph of that Beauty which ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilieſt incounter the Genius of thoſe <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris'es,</hi> who being to be Judges, the older they were, would be the leſs paſſionate in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably deciding the queſtion wheron the poſſeſſion not of an Aple, but of a Crown did depend. 'Twas a Spectacle indeed worthy to be ſeen by the whole world, to behold fourſcore exceeding handſome and nobly born virgins within one room, whoſe pomp, riches, quaintneſs of dreſs and apar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, added to their prerogatives of Nature, made up ſo pleaſing a miracle to the eyes of the lookers on, as they doubted whether what they ſaw was mortall or heavenly. 'Twas then apparently ſeen what womens induſtry can do in inventing rich &amp; coſtly apparell, and extravagant dreſſings to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by Art the worth of their native beauties, whilſt what the innocent want of experience in virgins could not doe, was by more cunning women by ſtudied Art effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with all their whole might. Here did ſome appeare with hair elaboratly wound up in Rings, part whereof was tied up with Ribbons, part artificially curld, which fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling careleſly upon the ſhoulders, and upon the cheeks, made them bluſh to be kiſt by ſo wanton hair. Others barbarouſly artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the treaſures of their hair wholly lockt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121609:5"/>up under a monopolizing turbant of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt linnen, ſhewd forth only ſome few fine threeds of refined gold; whence the worth and lovelineſs of the intire Maſs of thoſe hairs, which were vailed and hid, might be judged. Others on the contrary, prodigall and ambitious to divulge their Treaſure, gave them their naturall liberty to be plaid on by the windes, who being free diſpenſers thereof, afforded part of them to the thicker aire, that it might not annoy thoſe which were illuminated by the Sun-beams. I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not thoſe Roſes of Diamonds, Rubies, and a thouſand other Jewels, which crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the purity of thoſe fore-heads uſhering in the Orientall eyes: Nor yet thoſe great and pureſt Pearls which they wore at their eares and about their Alabaſter necks, and which wondred to ſee themſelves out-done in whiteneſſe; for I intend to ſpeak of beauty, not of the acceſſories thereof. I cannot notwithſtanding paſs over in ſilence the comelineſs of their aparrell, the Silkes wherof being taken from <hi>Perſia,</hi> &amp; the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall faſhions from the moſt effeminat Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, I know not whether they did receive from, or bequeath more lovelineſs to thoſe members which it was their good fortune to cover. In fine, on what ſide ſoever you could look, your eye incountred no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121609:6"/>but wonders. Faces compoſed of Lillies and mountain Roſes, boſomes of pureſt Alabaſter, lips of Coral, pearls ſhaped into teeth, Eyes brighter then the Sun, milky hands; ſuch and ſo many were the raviſhing graces, and comportments in this ſo fair aſſembly of Virgins, as mens minds confuſed with amazement, and thinking it not poſſible that thoſe could be real truths which ſeemed to be the miracles of beauty, they doubted whether the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity they ſaw were true, or but an Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The Embaſſadors who were to make choice, perceived then that it was not ſo eaſie as men believed, to judge of beauty, much leſs amongſt ſo numerous a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, where the underſtanding was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounded by comparing one with another, and where they were to ſatisfie anothers liking, and not their own inclination. To this was added, that their judgments might be abuſed by their curious Dreſſes, which ſometimes do not only mend but alter the defects of nature. They would not have known what to reſolve upon, had not one of them after much cogitation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, deſired that the Prince might be intreated, that all thoſe Virgins might be commanded once more to appear in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121609:6"/>but all of them clothed after one and the ſame manner with tranſparent vails, and looſe <hi>diſhevell</hi>'d hair, to the end that ſuch blemiſhes in the other parts of their bodies, covered by their Aparrel, dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, or were it but with the artificial pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their faces, might not traduce their judgment. This was agreed upon, in ſo much as ſome of the Virgins choſe rather to renounce the uncertain fortune of a Crown, then their innate modeſty, by ſuffering themſelves to be ſeen little leſs then naked. But though the number were leſſened, and all Artifices forbidden, yet would it not have been eaſie to make choice, had not a daughter of the Marquiſs of <hi>Filerno,</hi> named <hi>Niſſena,</hi> by ſuch vivaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as became a Queen, freed the judges of their doubt, to whom the glory and praiſe of Beauty did of moſt due belong. The Virgins being brought again into the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid place, the Embaſſadors hid behind ſome Arras, and peeping through certain holes, ſtood with wonder gazing now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one, now upon another of thoſe pillars of ſnow, when on the ſuddain <hi>Niſſena,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing ſomewhat before the reſt, with a maidenly bluſh, ſaid thus; <hi>She who deſires to Reigne, ought by her actions to make her ſelf appear worthy thereof. I, my Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121609:7"/>not leſs modeſt then your ſelves, will not be aſhamed to diſplay unto the Heavens the reallity of thoſe beauties, which they have pleaſed to beſtow on me: the gaining of a Kingdom is in queſtion, which cannot be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſ'd at a leſs rate, then by ſuffering our ſelves to be ſeen ſo, as upon ſuch an occaſion we need not to be aſhamed of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No leſs aſtoniſhed at the magnanimity of that generous action, then ſtruck with admiration to behold thoſe naked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amendable beauties, the Ambaſſadors ſtood awhile in ſuſpence, and afterwards ran to reverence her for their Queen, to whom nothing but the worſhip of the knee was wanting to make her the true I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of <hi>Venus.</hi> She being afterwards clad in her accuſtomed aparrel, and the fame of ſo noble an action being ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, <hi>Fermondo</hi>'s ſelf came to reverence her as a Queen: and the reſt of the young maids fruſtrate of their coveted fortune, bewail'd even with tears, the loſs of their vain hopes. One of them who raſher then the reſt, thought her ſelf much the handſomeſt of them all, taking it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the Crown of <hi>Cyprus</hi> was to be the <hi>Guiderdon</hi> of her beautie, imagined her ſelf already poſſeſt of the Scepter, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as ſhe had promiſed places and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121609:7"/>to divers of her kindred and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, which as ſhe affirm'd, ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd upon them by that King, over whom ſhe already pretended abſolute power. She, ſeeing <hi>Niſſena</hi> prefer'd before her, though ſhe died not, fel grievouſly ſick out of meer vexation, and in the heats of a violent fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which aſſailed her, fel into raving fits of commanding, and expecting to be ſerved and obeyed as a Queen: having after ſome months recovered her bodily health, ſhe could never recover the health of her mind, agitated with continual melancholy, which utterly clouding her underſtanding, brought her within a few years to her grave, with a fond imagination that ſhe was the Kings wife, and chief Commandreſſe of the Crown of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> Thus doth Ambition and vain glory finde always puniſhment in their own faults. The ſorrow of the other maids was ſomewhat allayd by rich and pretious Jewels, preſented unto them by the Ambaſſadors, as teſtimonies of the Kings munificencie. Publique rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cings were had through the whole Iſland for <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s preferment, whiles ſad <hi>Emeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> deeply in love with her, was he alone who amidſt the common rejoycings, made tryal of more then mortal ſufferings: He ſwounded at the firſt news that for her
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121609:8"/>beauties merit, ſhe was exalted to the throne of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and had aſſuredly died, had not grief ſupplyed the place of his ſoul, to keep him alive: the poor diſconſolate young man was ſo much the more unhappy, in that he ſaw himſelf in ſom ſort forc'd to aplaud her fortune, whoſe proſperity and greatneſſe he was bound to wiſh well unto, though to the prejudice of his own heart. He was now out of decency bound to change his love into obſervance, and yet was it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him who was in love, to force a paſſage from the one affection to the other, without the reſentments of a thouſand deaths. <hi>I rejoyce</hi> (ſaid he weeping) <hi>my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored</hi> Niſſena <hi>to ſee thee a Queen, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rejoyce, nor yet without breathing out my Soul, ſuffer, that thou being exalted to a Crown, art for ever to deprive me of any more ſeeing, ſerving, or obſerving thee: and yet my grieved heart muſt ſuffer it. O my too fair and too intirely beloved</hi> Niſſena! <hi>wherefore was not my love leſſe fervent, and you, why were not you leſſe fair; I ſhould not then be now thus tormented. Could my inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitious ſtars plot a greater misfortune for me? Give a Kingdoms Scepter to the Queen of my thoughts; to the end that I might for ever be by her abandoned and forgotten? Ah</hi> Emerino, <hi>ceaſe lamenting, be of good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121609:8"/>give way to Fortune, and be glad that thy beloved hath met with honour befitting her merit, and ſuch as thou thy ſelf art bound to deſire for her. Thou oughteſt to have foreſeen that Nature intended her for a Crown: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and be glad, for if thou rejoyceſt not in her happineſs, ſhe may juſtly believe thou didſt never love her. But alas! how can I be glad, if in her I have loſt all my joy, all my content? I will afflict my ſelf, yea as long as I live, but ſo as my mournfull complaints ſhall never arrive at my Faire ones Ear, nor in any the leaſt manner diſturbe her contentment in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing become a Queen. Courage, my Heart, let us ſeem to rejoyce with her: and for that ſhee may perhaps diſdain to hear me ſpeak, I will by Writing acquaint her with my ſouls affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Then taking a Pen, he wrote thus unto her:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>DIſdain not, I beſeech you, my long in vain adored <hi>NIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENA,</hi> to abaſe your Eyes ſo far in theſe your preſent Greatneſſes, as to read this Paper: Peruſe this laſt time the Characters of your formerly not forlorn <hi>EMERINO,</hi> who appears before you not in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121609:9"/>poſture of a Lover, but of an humble Servant, rejoycing to ſee you raiſed to that ſublime degree of Dignity; to which your ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conditions, and my perverſe Fortune hath raiſed you: For, my Fortune hath been miſerably unfortunate. But may your Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries be daily greater, though they coſt me my Life, if my Sorrows may not ſuffice; for I will never grieve thereat. Neither doe I now complain for that ſeconding the deſtiny and the immenſeneſs of your Merit, you have forſaken me to beſtow your ſelf upon a King: Yet muſt I needs be afflicted, to ſee my ſelf ſo unexpectedly abandoned by you, who by your Nuptials in vaine long pretended unto by me, are now going to make another happy. Goe notwithſtanding ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with all imaginable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121609:9"/>proſperity. May your Husband love you, the Nobles of your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome reverence you, the People bow unto you, the Heavens make your Womb fruitfull, and fill your Soul with Mirth: For my part, I ſhall remain amidſt my tormenting Paſſions, bewayling my being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of all Conſolation, ſave in as farr as my Afflictions prove the Effects of your felicity.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>EMERINO.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter cauſed ſome compaſſion in <hi>Niſſena,</hi> yet not ſuch as to be ſencibly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted therewith: Firſt, for that there had never been any ſuch correſpondency in love between her and <hi>Emerino,</hi> as though but in the condition of a privat Lady, might have neceſſitated her to be his: next, becauſe her heart was ſo poſſeſt with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ambition, as that it was incapable of any other paſſion. In fine, great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, if they do not totally change, they do at leaſt very much alter the minds
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121609:10"/>of whoſoever they be, much more a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans minde who ſuffers her ſelf eaſily to be carried away by Pride. After a few days ſhe went from <hi>Rhodes</hi> towards <hi>Cyprus,</hi> much honour'd by <hi>Fermondo,</hi> courted by many Ladies and Cavaliers, and accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by her kindred, a Gentleman being before ſent from the Embaſſadors to <hi>Thoas</hi> to acquaint him with their retun, and with their bringing a Beauty with them which they thought really worthy of him. He received the tidings with much content, though he had long kept his bed through much ſickneſs. Cauſing his Couſin <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo</hi> to be called unto him (who was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the deſceaſed <hi>Almira,</hi> and being ill dealt with by nature as being the third ſon, could no ways pretend to his Fathers Crown, and therefore entertained himſelf there in <hi>Thoas</hi> his Service) He commanded him to ſee four Gallies forthwith put in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, well furniſh'd with Arms, and that accompanied as became him, he ſhould prepare to go aboard, and in his ſtead to meet the new Queen. The Prince did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately obey the Kings Commands in all points, who charging him to make all haſte he could back, bad him farewell, and the mean while minded with all poſſible care his recovery: but being oppreſt all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121609:10"/>the next night with an unwilling, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome inward melancholy, he grew much worſe, and was found by the Phyſitians the next day in a high fit of a feaver, theſe were the preſages which foretold him that ſome other body was ordaind to eſpouſe <hi>Niſsena. Our ſouls (as I believe) partaking of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, foreſees, though obſcurely and by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known means, as well our proſperous as our fatall ſucceſses, every one having within him a certain beam or ſparkle of Prophetical light, either more or leſs, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Organs which ſubſerve the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doralboes</hi> Gallies being this mean while favour'd by proſperous windes, and by a quiet calm, came within two days in ken of the Embaſſadors Gallies. Great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of joy were made on all ſides; the aire was rent in two with the thunder of Canon, with the muſical noyſe of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and Drums, which were anſwered by the remote eccho's, reverberating applauſes to the glory of <hi>Niſsena,</hi> fill'd the Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors hearts with joy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Veſſels being come nearer, one did put forth from the midſt of thoſe of <hi>Doralbo's,</hi> which at firſt was thought to be a ſmall Pinace, &amp; was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards found to be a large Schalop, rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121609:11"/>trim'd with pureſt ſilver, and of ſuch a greatneſs as it contain'd within the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cave boſome thereof a <hi>Venus</hi> accompanied by <hi>Cupid,</hi> who in a ſmiling and rejoycing manner expreſſed his extraordinary glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by the frequent clapping and beating of his wings. The ſumptuous Engine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come ſo near the Gally wherein <hi>Niſſena</hi> was, as that the voice might be heard, the aire was fill'd with ſuch ſweet muſick, as the winds withholding themſelves at ſuch melody, breathed nothing but ſuch aires as proceeded from the Goddeſs her inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mouth, who made it plainly appear that ſhe had learn'd the harmony of the Sphears. The words of the ditty ſaid, <hi>That the Crown of</hi> Cyprus <hi>was more due to</hi> Niſſena <hi>then to</hi> Venus, <hi>who did as well yeild up unto her the Government of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as ſhe did the prize of Beautie.</hi> The two principal Gallies of either ſide boar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one another, <hi>Doralbo</hi> was he who firſt haſted to proſtrate himſelf before <hi>Niſſena,</hi> as Queen, he being followed by twelve young Ladies, ſix Matrons, and four and twenty Cavaliers, ſo richly atired as refin'd Gold was the leaſt conſiderable material thereof: great ſtore of footmen and pages in ſumptuous liveries were not wanting,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121609:11"/>who when they firſt ſaw <hi>Niſſena,</hi> fell all upon their knees at a good diſtance off, whereunto ſhe correſponded with ſuch Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as ſhe ſeem'd to be born, not aſſum'd to a Scepter. The Prince leading her by the arm, ſhe paſt into his Gallie, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cover'd on the outſide from the Poop to the fore deck with gold and Cryſtall, with ſails of Purple ſilk, and lin'd within with green Arras intermingled and border<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about with gold, appear'd a ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpectacle to the eye. The lighting of Artillery, and the noiſe of Canon trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and deafning the air; which volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous ſmoke and vain glorious noiſe, proved that praiſes given to human great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are nothing elſe in reality but wind and ſmoke. Amongſt ſo many lovely and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable objects, there was none more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of ſight, or which took the eye more then the fair <hi>Niſſena,</hi> who was the boundeur of all ſight, the wonder of all minds, and cauſed agitation in all hearts: her decent affability, fitting vivacity, gratious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment without affectation, and her maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical aſpect without ſeverity, increaſed love and reverence towards her in every one. They came happily within ſight of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> where they were forced to ſtay at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121609:12"/>Anchor half a day and a whole night by reaſon of a Weſterly Wind which blew from land a little too briskly; at laſt they entred the Haven early the next morning, where all thoſe ſignes of welcome, and both publique and privat demonſtrations of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and rejoycing vvhich are accuſtomari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed either by vvay of flattery or reſpect, by ſubjects tovvards their Soveraigns did abound. Nothing vvas vvanting but the preſence of the King, vvho though cured, yet oppreſt by melancholy, could not abandon his bed; the skilfulleſt Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians not knovving vvhether to attribute the cauſe to any outvvard or invvard diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. He affirm'd he found his heart op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt and overcome by extremity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, it being incapable of ſo immenſe a joy, and thus taking but little nouriſhment he reſted unquietly in the night ſeaſon, and in the day time vvas troubled vvith ſtrange diſtractions of mind; yet variety of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn ſports and publique feaſts were not forgotten: wherein it was obſerved by the vviſer ſort as a prodigie of future evils, that a guilded woodden ſtatue of the Kings was unavoidably burnt to aſhes, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how or cauſe vvhy being never able to be learnt. <hi>Niſſena</hi> conſidered theſe inau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicious
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121609:12"/>occurrences, and ſeeing the ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of her fortune thus troubled at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firſt beginning, ſhe was highly therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all afflicted, yet did ſhe with all the care ſhe could, conceal her inward ſorrow from others. After five days ſpace the face of affairs altered, the King forgoing his bed, with a pretty competency of health, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect chearfulneſs, who viſited by his Bride, at the firſt encounter of her brighteſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, was like to die for meer Joy; ſhe appear'd handſomer unto him then he could have conceived her to be, ſo as quite alter'd even to his very voice, he met her and with open arms imbraced her, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately ſaying, <hi>Welcome my deareſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in whom I am to be happy. Good Gods! of whom have the</hi> Rhodian <hi>Mothers learnt to bring forth daughters ſo beautifull? bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the hour my dear</hi> Niſſena <hi>that firſt brought thee into the world, bleſſed be thoſe ſwadling clouts wherein thou wer't bound, thoſe breaſts that gave thee ſuck, but more bleſſed be that Fortune which gave thee into my poſſeſſion: I will be King of</hi> Cyprus, <hi>and thou ſhalt be my Queen.</hi> Not uttering one word, ſhe anſwered with the tongue of baſhfulneſs, which ſhewed her to be no leſs fair within then without. The King ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121609:13"/>her afterwards ſit down by his ſide, Preſſing hard and often kiſſing her hand, asked her divers queſtions, to which ſhe anſwered with ſuch modeſty, as he might eaſily diſcern the vivacity of her wit, and the wiſdom of her underſtanding. Had not the many conſultations of the learned Doctors who tended his cure denyed him, he would that night have celeberated his Marriage with his beloved. Great is the miſery of great ones, who can ſeldom compaſs what they moſt covet, it not being in their will to eat, or take their delight, according to their own pleaſure, but by the good liking of ſuch as do either flatter them, or ſuch as would ſeem wiſe, and who do ſometime hate their contentments. The Phyſitians ordered that <hi>Thoas</hi> ſhould keep a ſpare but nouriſhing diet for a good ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days, and that he ſhould be kept from hearing of any news, or from ſeeing of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing which might incumber his mind with any ſort of affection or paſſion. He punctually obey'd them deſirous to be ſoon rid of their rigour; every hour appearing an age unto him till he ſhould be made happy in the Embraces of his <hi>Niſſena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings recovery of his health, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the approaching celebration of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121609:13"/>his marriage, did ſo rejoyce his ſubjects, as the whole Kingdome gave publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat teſtimony of their gladſomneſs. Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, and Fire-works by night, Baales, Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Turneys, Barriers, Theaters, and Scenes were every where had with much ſumptuouſneſs. The Queen being preſent at the greateſt part of them, was by the judgement of all men ſtill the moſt praiſed and moſt admired object; which <hi>Doralbo</hi> did prove and approve of more then any other, who from that fatall minute that he ſaw her, taken with her beauty, fell mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in love with her, his flames being the more hot and devouring, by how much he kept them the more concealed; he burnt, and knowing the inconvenience and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his fire, he had oft and in ſundry wiſe endeavoured to extinguiſh, at leaſt to appeaſe it. His own heart was onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious thereof, he durſt not ſo much as ſigh, leſt being diſcovered by the winds, they might communicate his ardency to the ambiating air. If ſomtimes his looks did in the preſence of the beloved <hi>Niſſena,</hi> betray the ſecret of his thoughts, by ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelves to feed too greedily upon her reverenced beauty, he had a puniſhment ready prepared for them, by making them
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121609:14"/>fall languiſhing and without life upon the ground: he durſt neither aſpire unto, nor hope for correſpondency, the one and the other of them being unlawfull and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; he loved, and knew not to what end, unleſſe it were to ſuffer under torment. Whilſt he conſumed away amidſt theſe painfull ſtraits, it happened that waiting one afternoon upon the Queen (on whom by the Kings command he continually atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) in the little Court of Statues, ſo called by reaſon of the abundance of ſtately Scul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures wherewith it was adorned, he ſtood with her, accompanied with ſome few La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, beholding the ſtatue of <hi>Hercules</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing <hi>Anteus,</hi> cut out in ſtone, when they might hear from the neighbouring parts a noyſe of out-cries and weapons; at the ſame time came in a groom of the ſtable with a face as pale as Death, who cried out aloud, <hi>Fly, Fly and ſave your ſelves, for a fierce Tygre eſcaped from the uſuall incloſed place wherein he was kept, roaves hereabouts, killing and deſtroying as many as he meets withall; ſave your ſelves, I ſay, for he will be ſhortly in this Court, and we ſhall be all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably dead.</hi> The Women with their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries, the Men with their ſwords in hand, but all of them affrighted and confuſed, ran
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121609:14"/>ſome one way ſome another, ſeeking how to eſcape the danger which threatned them ſo ſorely. Onely dauntleſs <hi>Doralbo,</hi> griping hard his Sword, and looking upon <hi>Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſena</hi> whom he might ſee look pale, holding her hands out towards him to implore aid; ſaid, <hi>Be not afraid Madam, the fierceſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of</hi> Hercania, <hi>came they all in a Troop, much leſs this one, ſhall not offend you, whilſt you have</hi> Doralbo <hi>by your ſide: May my death prove your ſafeguard, dear Madam: For how happy ſhall he be to dye for you once only, who doth ſo daily?</hi> This being ſaid, he went ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtily to defend the entrance into the little Court, where he had not been long, when he might ſee one come running, who could ſcarcely draw his breath; who with much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe told, how the unwary Beaſt following the trace of a Maſtiffe Dog which he had wounded, was got into a houſe, the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows whereof being well furniſht with ſtrong iron Barres, and the gate vvell fortified and ſhut by a Souldier more cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious and vviſe then vvere the reſt, vvas there made a priſoner, having ſlain onely his keeper, and two of the Warders. At the hearing of this happy news every one took breath, and a number of armed men coming in, they vvere by <hi>Doralbo</hi> diſmiſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121609:15"/>to their ſeverall imployments, vvhilſt he, the Ladies, and the other Gentlemen ſtood diſcourſing vvith the Queen of the danger vvhich they had eſcaped. Being vvaited upon to her lodging, ſhe obſerved how the Prince, taking leave at his parting from her, fixt a look in her eyes, vvhich though it vvere but momentary, and as it vvere by ſtealth, ſeemed as if it ſaid, <hi>I for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent depart from you my adored lights, but I leave all my thoughts depoſited with you.</hi> At this inſtant ſhe call'd to mind the words which he let fall in the little Court, then when he exhorted her not to be afraid of the Tyger; and though at firſt ſhe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them onely as a complement from a Generous and Noble Prince, yet remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that ſhe had heard him ſay, <hi>It ſhould be happy for him to die for her once onely, for whom he died daily:</hi> She thought the words taſted more of affection then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement. Thus from his words and from his looks ſhe drew two infallible conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that he was in love with her; and though as then ſhe ſhew'd no ſignes of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, yet was ſhe not ſcandalized with his love, every woman being deſirous to be beloved, if not out of wantonneſſe, yet out of ambition; ſhe reſolved notwithſtanding
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121609:15"/>to curb that in him which ſhe judged ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be a motion or cuſtome of youth, then an affection grounded in ſo ſhort a time. The King quitt her of theſe thoughts, who came to rejoyce with her for her having happily eſcaped the late danger ſhe was in, he had underſtod the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines from <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who waiting upon him to the Queens lodgings (he never omitting any occaſion of being where ſhe was) ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee himſelfe received by her with a leſs pleaſing countenance, &amp; more grave maner then accuſtomed, he preſently cal'd to mind the words which had eſcaped his mouth through the force of his affection then when he prepared with hazard of his own life to ſave hers from the Tygers imminent fury, judging ſhe might have taken offence thereat; ſo as he had no ſooner waited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the King, but that retiring himſelfe into his Cloſet, full of paſſion and griefe, he threw himſelf down upon a Couch, and fixing his eys upon the ground, he by many deep-fetcht-ſighes, uſher'd in theſe lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>Unfortunate <hi>Doralbo!</hi> What heynous fault haſt thou committed? What was this thy raſhneſs? Why didſt thou preſume ſo much? Audacious tongue, why did not I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121609:16"/>rather pluck thee from out my throat, then ſuffer thee to ſay in the preſence of <hi>Niſſena, That I die daily for her?</hi> Alas! the fault was neither thine nor mine; I did not then think to diſcover my affection, neither didſt thou intend to ſpeak it: 'Twas my heart which without adviſing with my underſtanding, did dictate thoſe words unto thee: 'tis thou my heart who wer't the Traytor: I cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly would never have ſaid it, nor will I ever ſay it more, I will rather die a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times. He would have lamented lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, had not his exceſſive griefe by making him almoſt ſenſleſs, hindred him from ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more. So as after having a long while with much perturbance of mind nouriſht his ſufferings and fancies, he call'd in his ſervants, and making himſelfe unready, he faigning to be weary, went to bed. What reſt he took that night, let them tell it for me, who train'd up in the School of Love, have reall affections, and know what tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſuch accidents doe cauſe. He ſlept but a little, &amp; if ſomtimes though but for a very ſmal ſpace he ſtole a nap, he forthwith ſeemed to have <hi>Niſſena</hi> before him, who much incenſt, and in a threatning manner reproved his raſhneſs. As he would have proſtrated himſelfe before her feet to ask
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121609:16"/>her pardon, he awakened, and found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe void of the hopes of asking, much more of obtaining it. His body and mind were ſorely agitated all the night, ſave that towards the break of day falling aſleep, he dream'd he ſaw a very handſome young woman, cloathed all in green, who ſeemed ſmilingly to ſay unto him, <hi>Awake from ſleep and ſorrow dull</hi> Doralbo, <hi>for</hi> Niſſena <hi>attends thee, purſue to ſerve and love with loyalty and conſtancy; for after the tempeſts of thy troubles, thy love ſhall find a ealm and quiet Haven to reſt in.</hi> This being ſaid, the pleaſing ſhadow vaniſht, and he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what eaſed of his vexatious thoughts, leapt out of bed, and as ſoon as he was ready, he haſted to the Queens Antichamber, where deſirous to viſit her, and to wiſh her a good day, he was anſwered otherwiſe then formerly, that he muſt be pleaſed to attend a while, till ſuch time as her women had dreſt her head, and put on her Jewels. This was a deadly wound to the ſoul of the ſuſpitious Prince, &amp; yet he patiently &amp; obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diently obſerved her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands, not giving any the leaſt ſhew of diſturbance. As he this mean while walked with her Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain, the Lord <hi>Angria,</hi> he wondred to hear himſelf thus ſpoken unto by the Baron.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121609:17"/>What thinks your Highneſs, Sir, of the ſtrange accidents which happened the laſt night? and what ſtrange accidents, replied <hi>Doralbo?</hi> I know nothing ſave onely that ſomwhat wearied I haſted to bed ſooner then uſuall, and was all night troubled with a thouſand dreams and fantaſies. Doe you mock me, reply'd the Baron? and looking <hi>Doralbo</hi> in the face, and finding his looks to expreſs rather a deſire of information then any mockery, he preſt him again, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Doe not you indeed know vvhat befell the Queen? At theſe vvords the Prince could not but ſeem ſomewhat troubled; his blood haſtening preſently from his heart to his face, ſo as with a panting heart he added, I vow unto you upon the vvord of a Prince, I know nothing; but I beſeech you acquaint me quickly with it. It vvas not yet two a clock at night (ſaid the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton) when one of my Footmen gave me di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers letters directed to the Queen, vvhich I preſently conveyed unto her: much time vvas not paſt, vvhen ſhe, moleſted in mind, cauſed her Aunt <hi>Eurania</hi> to be called unto her, and preſently afterward thoſe two Gentlemen her Coſen-germans, who had accompanied her from <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and having given expreſs order, that no one whoſoever
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121609:17"/>ſhould be ſuffered to come in, ſhe entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned herſelfe a good while in diſcourſe vvith them. I vvas afterwards vvilled that by all means poſſible I ſhould acquaint the King, that his humbleſt ſervant <hi>Niſſena,</hi> did moſt earneſtly deſire that his Majeſty would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly afford her audience. I vvas much aſtoniſhed at the hearing hereof, but I had nothing to doe but to obey.</p>
            <p>The King had betane himſelf to his reſt, which notwithſtanding he gave command that the Queen might be permitted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whenſover ſhe pleaſed; who accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied by her Aunt and her two Couſens, entred the Kings Chamber, and in a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, but very ſad manner kneeld down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Majeſties bed, who had raiſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up to welcome her, and confounding her words with her tears and ſobs, ſhe thus expreſt her inward ſorrow; I very well knew ſince my firſt coming from <hi>Rhodes,</hi> O <hi>Thoas,</hi> how unworthy I was to be your wife; but I knew not, nor could I imagin it poſſible, that a King whoſe fame is ſo glorious throughout the whole world, would go about to abuſe a poor ſilly young Maid, who though ſhe be not deſcended from Kings, hath yet in her the blood of the no ignoble houſe of the Marquiſs of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121609:18"/>
               <hi>Falerno,</hi> who at all times and upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions have always prefer'd their honour before their lives: Such a one was I born, as I can very well by my death waſh away with my blood any the leaſt ſhadows of ſhame which may hitherto have ſullied my reputation. When I came to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> I came in condition of your Majeſties wife, not of your Concubine, your ſelf knows it full well, The Kingdoms of <hi>Cyprus</hi> and of <hi>Rhodes</hi> knows it: If I have been ſtrangely deceived, I am no ways guilty of the deceit: I might juſtly deſerve all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of puniſhment, and might be eſteemed guilty, if I ſhould tarry any longer here, whither being come to live as your ſervant and conſort, I am advertiſed I muſt live your whore. Sir! I beg your leave to be gon: ſuffer me, O King, to return to that Climat where people are born as innocent as here, for in caſe you ſhould not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me ſo to do, I ſhall ſend my ſoul ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whither elſe.</p>
            <p>He who had all this while with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and troubled aſpect patiently liſten'd unto her, being able to hold no longer, cryed out, What dreams be theſe my Queen? who is that hath poſſeſt you with theſe apprehenſions, injurious to my
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121609:18"/>Crown and to your merit? ſince when is it that you have been my Concubine, and not my true wife? Liſten unto me. If e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I was poſſeſt with thought any ways the leaſt prejudicial to you, and if I be any ways conſcious, or but conſenting in very imagination to what you mention, let the heavens hurl down thunder upon me, let me be puniſht by Omnipotency, let the earth ſwallow me up, and may hel take me. I, who have always preſerv'd my faith invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable to all men, ſhall I maculate it to your prejudice, who next my Honour, are the only object for whom I would yeild up my Kingdom, ſhed my bloud, and loſe my life? Is it I that muſt betray you? have not my paſt actions ſufficiently witneſſed to the whole World (and to your ſelf, which troubles me moſt) the candor and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of my ſoul? O if I ſhall ever know who that wretched villain is, that hath plotted theſe my vexations, my revenge ſhall make him an example to all ages. For what remains, be of good comfort my <hi>Niſſena,</hi> for you ſhall ſoon ſee that you have been deceived in thinking your ſelf deceived by me who honour you. Or you ſhall be Queen of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> or I will lay down the Scepter thereof. Reach me pen &amp;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121609:19"/>paper. Then calling in for divers Noble men &amp; Gentlemen of the Court, &amp; me amongſt the reſt, he in their preſence under-writ a blank paper and ſigning it with his Regal Seal, take this, ſaid he, my Queen. Write in this whatever tyes or agreements you ſhall think fit to ratifie our marriage; and if I do ever deceive <hi>Niſſena,</hi> be you all wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to the whole world of my infamy, and declare me unworthy either to Reigne or live. At theſe lively expreſſions of true affection and candid Loyalty, the Queen for awhile ſtood immovable; then weeping for tenderneſs, ſhe obſequiouſly took the Kings hand in hers, and humbly kiſſing it, ſaid; Pardon me Sir, for I am betray'd: pardon I beſeech you the offence which you might juſtly take at me for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering my ſelf to be too eaſily perſwaded that you were guilty of a fault which now I ſee to have been ſo far from your magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous and Princely heart. This, Sir, was that that betraid me, and therewithall ſhe gave him a Letter which ſhe had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Packet from <hi>Rhodes,</hi> the ſence whereof was: That a perſonage much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate to her, compaſſionating that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune which had carryed her from her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, &amp; from her country, to the end
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121609:19"/>that in her ſo flouriſhing age, and indow'd with ſo great beauty and worth ſhe was likely to be groſely abuſed and deceived by anothers barbarous luſt, he was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through pitty of her misfortunes to adveriſe her, that <hi>Thoas</hi> feigning by ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ways and pretences to take her to be his wife, nouriſhing her with vain hopes, would enjoy her as a whore. That he did the rather acquaint her with theſe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, ſince by doing ſo he did ſecond the will of Heaven, which having till then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted the King with ſickneſs, ſhew'd how it did abhor his miſchievous machinations; but that being now recovered he would not be long in bereaving her of her virginity. That ſhe ſhould therefore ſpeedily flie from <hi>Cyprus</hi> if ſhe would keep that reputation untainted which had for ſo many ages made famous the Houſe of <hi>Falerno,</hi> or if ſhe deſired to render her ſelf glorious for having wiſely deluded the luſtful ends of a treacherous King. Thou art the wicked Traitor, who e're thou art, cry'd <hi>Thoas,</hi> who poſſeſt with I know not what Infernal fury, indeavoureſt to ſubvert my quiet: but if I may ever know who thou art, thy head ſhal juſtly pay for theſe thy baſe and infamous ſtratagems. Then obſerving the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121609:20"/>Letter to be without a name or date; O, <hi>Niſſena,</hi> ſaid he, you were too eaſie in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting the ſlightneſs of a Letter written by one who was aſhamed to own it! if every one would believe ſuch deceitful Letters, the way would be made too eaſie for wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men by their inventions to undoe the World. Their minds are blinded who credit a blind paper when it contains no Truths which do appear palpable to the ſence, or viſible to the eye. I wil not not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding for this time chide you: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto your Lodgings comforted, and ſecure of my Faith. She trembling all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, alledg'd many reaſons for her too eaſie belief, at laſt confeſſing it to be a fault, ſhe as a favour, beg'd either to be puniſh'd or pardon'd by the King, who diſmiſſing her with a kiſs, ſent for two of his privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors and long diſcuſt the matter with them: it was reſolved that it was worthy of no ſmall conſideration, ſince the indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour tended to the diverting of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Marriage, upon which the ſucceſſion depending, it conſequently inſued that ſome one or other, out of ſome important ends, were glad to ſee the Crown without iſſue: though it afterwards appear'd that they were evidently unwiſe, who had in their
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121609:20"/>vaſt thoughts gon about to hinder <hi>Niſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>'s Marriage, whilſt it was not likely that the King would want other Wives, to whoſe marriage ſo many great Princeſſes had aſpired, and in particular two daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the dreaded King <hi>Nicaſter</hi> of <hi>Loria:</hi> 'twas thought that ſome of the chief men of <hi>Rhodes</hi> in love with <hi>Niſſena,</hi> might out of an amorous deſperation, have indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd ſo vain an enterprize, but whoſoever it were, his Majeſtie was to learn by this ſmall accident, to have a better eye upon any the leaſt occurrences then he formerly had had: The manner of the character and the paper being afterwards conſidered, the firſt was unkn own to them all, the latter was knovvn by the mark to be made in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus.</hi> I being ſomewhat ſeverely queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned from whom I had received thoſe pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets which I had cauſed to be delivered to the Queen, anſwered, from one of my footmen, who being ſuddenly ſent for, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that they were given unto him at the firſt entrance into the Hall, by one whoſe habit ſpoke him to be a Mariner, and that he ſaid he had received them from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a Pinnace of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> who was come the day before into the Haven, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs command to take order that they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121609:21"/>might be delivered at the Court. The Maſter of the Pinnace being found at his Lodging, he was forthvvith impriſoned, and threatened with the Rack: being maſter'd by fear, he anſvver'd a thouſand things little to the purpoſe to what was ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſo that all that they could draw from him was, that the Letters which he brought from <hi>Rhodes,</hi> were given him at his coming from thence by a kinſman of his vvho vvas a ſervant to the Family of the Marquiſs of <hi>Falerno.</hi> He was not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding ſtill detained in priſon, till the Kings further pleaſure ſhould be knovvn, vvhich vvas, that he ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer torture: Prince <hi>Doralbo</hi> at the recitall hereof ſuffered inwardly divers agitations of minde; and asked many queſtions of the Baron, that he might punctually inform himſelf of every the leaſt particular. It was no wonder if he appeared paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly curious, whilſt an intereſt was treated of, wherein his heart was concern'd; but he was interrupted by the arrival of one of the Gentlemen of <hi>Thoas</hi> his Chamber, who gave order in his Majeſties name, that the Queen ſhould be inform'd, that at her beſt leaſure ſhe might go to the Temple to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt at the Sacrifices which were to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121609:21"/>her marriage. <hi>Doralbo</hi> taking his leave of the Baron of <hi>Angria,</hi> went to the Kings Lodgings, who by reaſon of his laſt nights waking, or perhaps through the agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his minde, had a very ſore fit of a Feaver, and having done his obeiſance to him, the King asked him how he did, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I would not trouble your reſt the laſt night, underſtanding that being weary, you had made more haſte to bed then uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; but you muſt this morning take ſome pains for me. Be it your care that you command the Lord preſident in my name, that he publickly in the Temple Marry <hi>Niſſena</hi> in my behalf, ſince it pleaſeth the Gods to deny me the happineſs of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her; and that when he ſhal have Crowned her Queen, he do in the name of all my Vaſſals ſwear fealty to her, whilſt I the mean while wraſtle with the fit that is come upon me. The reſt I took (ſaid <hi>Doralbo</hi>) was in an unluckie hour, ſince it hindred me from ſerving your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, whereat I am much grieved; I wiſh I could as wel ſuffer thoſe pains inſtead of you, which you now undergoe, as your goodneſs aſſures me that you wil accept of my preſent readineſs to ſerve you, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the fault unwillingly committed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121609:22"/>of not waiting upon your Majeſty the laſt night. This being ſaid, the Prince went to obey the Kings commands. <hi>Mintan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> a man of mean birth, of a great under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, quick at the managing of Affairs, but proud, and of a ſtrangely turbulent and ſeditious mind was then Lord Preſident; to which degree of honor his riches had brought him, by means whereof he marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great Lady, and wrought himſelf into a very noble kindred, and ſo got into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and preferment with the King. His wife died when ſhe had brought him a ſon named <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> who by reaſon of his raſh and troubleſome conditions, was the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal of all <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> though his ranting, and his Fathers Authority made him be feared and reverenced by all men. <hi>Mintaurus</hi> was one of thoſe who was diſpleaſed at <hi>Thoas</hi> his reſolution of marrying <hi>Niſſena;</hi> ſo as hearing himſelf commanded by the King to marry her in his behalf, and having Crowned her, to ſwear Fealty to her in the name of all the people, he could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear giving ſome teſtimonies of diſpleaſure; yet not making any reply, he buckel'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the buſineſs, crafty <hi>Doralbo</hi> was aware of it, but without more adoe went to wait on her, from whoſe rigid or pleaſing counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121609:22"/>he with a beating &amp; doubtfull heart expected the Deſtiny of his affection. She came forth, and by her indifferent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment made him know that he was not more particularly favour'd by her then were others, but rather in ſomewhat a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and diſdainfull manner ſtudied to keep her eyes from incountring with his; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did ſhe ſo often ſmile upon him as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſhe had done.</p>
            <p>Unfortunate <hi>Doralbo!</hi> with how many Darts vvas thy ſoul pierced? He aſſiſted at the Sacrifices, and forgetting the ſacred Altars, he adored that Idol, from whom inſtead of favours he expected killing frowns. <hi>Niſſena</hi> being married by <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurus,</hi> and crowned Queen, ſhe returned to the Palace, and deſired ſhe might have leave to viſit her husband, and to thank him for having raiſed her to that degree whereby ſhe was for ever bound to be his Servant and Companion. But he being in the height of his Fit, vvas not in a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to receive any Ambaſſie that day; no not ſo much as viſits. The next night he grew better, and took ſome reſt; ſo as the next morning he vvas able to get out of Bed, and to dine with his Queen, feeding much more greedily with his eys then with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121609:23"/>his mouth. The Court was full of ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting and contentment: Onely Prince <hi>Doralbo,,</hi> though he knew it misbecame him not to appeare more joyfulll then uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all among theſe univerſall rejoycings, could not keep the ſad Enſignes of inward me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy from appearing in his pale face, which fretted him even to the heart: his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary ſadneſs being perceived by all, the Queen not many dayes after was alſo aware thereof, to boot that it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly whiſpered about by the Ladies and Gentlemen. She had compaſſion on him, and to give him ſome comfort, and ſince the cauſe of ſo great a melancholy might not for a long time be ſeen into, ſhe began by degrees to be more gracious unto him, ſometimes cheering him with pleaſing ſmiles, ſometimes with partiall lookes, ſo as ſhortly returning to his former vivacity, he became not onely cheerfull as before, but was the ioy and delight of the whole Court. O the fondneſs of vain Lovers, who think themſelves made happy by a ſmile or look, which ſometimes is but ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall, and not willingly confer'd, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſometimes not without fraud; and are again made miſerable by another look, which they interpret as ſcorn, or ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121609:23"/>which may peradventure be a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning invitation to ſpur them on to be more ardent in their loves. <hi>Niſſena</hi> imparted theſe favours unto him ſo as they were no ways prejudiciall to the cand or of her faith which ſhe had plighted and vowed to <hi>Thoas:</hi> For from the time ſhe had tane upon her the yoke of marriage (though it were not yet conſummate) not ſo much as one misbecomming thought ſullied the inward purity of that breaſt which wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed outwardly immaculate innocency. She, I know not whether out of favour to him, or ſollicited by her naturall genius to read bookes of Chevalry, deſired him to provide her ſome fitting for her to read, that ſhe might paſs away the tedious hours of that ſeaſon which was now hotter then uſuall, though it was alwayes very hot under the Climate of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> He interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the honor of this command as a favour from the prodigall Heavens; and his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding being inlightned by blind love, which infuſeth ſubtilty into the moſt rough hewen minds, much more into ſuch as are quick and airy; he furniſht her with many books, the leaves whereof he had in ſome places cunningly turn'd down, where amorous affections are by ingenious
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121609:24"/>Writers expreſſed, whereby he diſcovered his paſſions to her who was their adored occaſion. <hi>Niſſena</hi> being quick of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, finding <hi>Doralbo's</hi> cunning, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red back his books unto him, folded down in like manner in other leaves, whereby he might underſtand and receive ſuch anſwers, as ſometimes excited hope in him, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reproved him of boldneſs. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Lover was herewithall ſo fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as he pretended to no other food or reward of his love. The King this mean while would needs have the Queen (who was now ſatiated with Feaſts, Turnys, and Tiltings) honour a Theater with her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, whereon the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Martaſſes,</hi> who with great fervency had deſired this favour, cauſed an excellent Stage-play to be acted. She went thither, having on her a veſture given her that day by her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, contrived and woven with <hi>Amianto,</hi> a pretious ſtone which is ſpun like threed; of which, as of other Jewels and Minerals, the Mines of <hi>Cyprus</hi> are very fruitfull; ſo as Beams being caſt abroad on every ſide by the reverberation of lights, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned the Theater, <hi>Niſſena</hi> ſemed to be the Sun of Beauty. Poor <hi>Doralbo!</hi> How many and how great ſplendors wer't thou
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121609:24"/>to reſiſt, to keep the eyes of thy mind unda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeled? The Play took all the Auditory exceedingly, being repreſented with ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sceans and inventions, ſutable to the Marqueſs his generous minde; but the Prince was chiefly pleaſed, (becauſe it made moſt for his purpoſe) with the fall of an unfortunate Lover, who deſperatly threw himſelfe from the top of a Mountain into the Sea, and to all appearance ſeemed to be therein drowned. <hi>Niſſena</hi> was a little moved at this ſpectacle, as ſhe witneſſed, by ſaying, <hi>Poor wretch! Since thou wer't onely guilty of too much love, thou didſt not deſerve ſo miſerable a death. Doralbo</hi> let not this occaſion ſlip without making his uſe of it, being already become ſo bold, as he durſt reply unto the Queen, <hi>Good Gods! How is it poſsible your Majeſty ſhould commiſerate one drowned in the water, and not be any thing at all concern'd in him who is conſumed in flames?</hi> And <hi>who is he</hi> (replied ſhe) <hi>who is thus conſumed? I ſee none hereabouts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vironed with fire.</hi> Ah (ſaid the Prince with a trembling voyce) <hi>you ſee him too well, but will not vouchſafe to look upon him. 'Tis I that am that wretch, who in love with you, would a thouſand times have breathed forth my Soul, had not my life been miraculouſly
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121609:25"/>preſerved by your more then humane Image, which is imprinted in my Heart. Diſdain not, O my Goddeſs, that I adore you; for I know how to doe it, without any blemiſh to your honour, prejudice to your reputation, or offence to my Soveraigne Lord</hi> Thoas, <hi>I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to nothing elſe, nor doe I ought deſire, but that I may be permitted to adore you whilſt I ſhall live, and that you will ſuffer it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſdain; I will doe what becomes your greatneſs, and my condition; be not you therewithall ſcandalized, moſt mighty Queen, if you would have me live.</hi> And here, with a broken ſigh, he ſtopped, expecting his ſentence of life or of death from the mouth of his beloved. She ſomwhat bluſhing, anſwered, <hi>That if the love he talked of were of any other temper then what he had ſayd, he might doe well to leave the vain and raſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize of loving her; but that if it were true that he knew to love like a true Prince, and Gentleman, in termes circumſcribed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the confines of that integrity and faith, which ſhe intended to preſerve immaculate to her husband, ſhe was pleaſed with his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that he might reſt aſſured of like cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondency in her, whilſt his thoughts ſhould continue thus modeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the beginnings of that Love
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121609:25"/>which not knowing how to get entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her chaſt boſom, went thus by piecemeal inſinuating it ſelf inſenſibly into her heart. Thou ſhalt ſhortly ſee <hi>Niſſena</hi> and be aware that affections enter our ſouls as it were by ſtealth, that they may afterwards in proceſs of time become Tyrants. Theſe diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes might paſs freely between them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being obſerv'd or liſtn'd unto, the Queens chair being placed ſomewhat high, and the Prince ſtanding cloſe by her on foot, whoſe ſoul was ſo filled with joy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this lucky incounter, as whereas former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he periſht through affliction, he now was almoſt kill'd with content; which was a little leſſen'd in him, by hearing how that <hi>Thoas,</hi> who grew daily better in his health, would by conſummation of his marriage, reap <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s Virginity; and though the knowledge of the unjuſtneſs of this his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet did in a great meaſure mitigate his for row, yet did it not keep him from ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation of mind as did imbitter all his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment. The King who ſeemd to be on the mending hand, and almoſt perfectly reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, did much ſolicit the Phyſitians, that he might now be permitted freely to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his beloved wife within his arms, which they had promiſed him to give way
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121609:26"/>unto within four days; in which interim of time he fell into a dangerous relaps, with very ſmall hope of ever recovering. There came unto his Majeſtie likewiſe at this time, an expreſs diſpatch away in haſte from the Conſuls of the Town of <hi>Siari,</hi> informing him, that great part of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery of the Commonwealth of <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta</hi> had in an inſolent and barbarous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner begun to prejudice them, by killing their men and firing their Countrey, which cauſed them to flie unto the wiſdom and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Majeſtie for ſuccour and repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to theſe great evils. That many of their neighbours and Soldiers drawn out of the adjacent Gariſons, had valiantly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Enemy; but that 'twas hard for a few men without any Commanders in chief, or good Warlick Diſcipline, long to reſiſt a multitude of armed men, provided with all things fitting to fight. That they had not as yet taken any Walled Towns, but only two Villages, wherein they had fortified themſelves, and went on deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the corn which was already almoſt ripe throughout all thoſe fruitfull fields.</p>
            <p>The King was highly afflicted at this news, preſaging this to be the preludium of his death, ſo as calling together his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121609:26"/>of State that morning, after they had conſidered the buſineſs, 'twas joyntly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, that all poſſible forces ſhould be preſently raiſed to reſiſt theſe firſt inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; That the mean while order and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation ſhould be taken for all Occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that the King ſhould in his due time name the Heads and chief Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Army, the charge of providing Arms was confer'd upon the Count <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> of <hi>Monagria,</hi> with Orders that the Kings Exchequer being immediately open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Drums ſhould beat up, and people ſhould be taken into pay, who joyned to the other Soldiers that were in Gariſon, and ſuch as might be drawn out of the Gallies, without much weakening the Maritin for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſhould be ready to march at an hours warning: in a ſhort ſpace an Army was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of 8000 foot and 2500 horſe, all of them Soldiers well enough appointed, but little experienc'd in Military affairs, for not only the Arms, but the very minds of the whole Kingdome were as it were ruſted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by means of long peace. Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo</hi> was by the King declared General. <hi>Filarbo,</hi> one of <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s Couſens, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant General, and his Brother <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> General of the Horſe. Other Commands
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121609:27"/>and Places were confer'd to other Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Gentlemen according to the Kings pleaſure, who knew very well the worth and abilities of all his Subjects. At the very inſtant that <hi>Doralbo</hi> received the place of Generall, he began to exerciſe his Command, fighting againſt his own thoughts, which in a rebellious manner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to mutiny againſt him. He eſteemed that preferment a miſery, not an honour, which by keeping him far from <hi>Niſſena,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided him from himſelf: but knowing that of neceſſity he was preſently to obey, he prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for departure, not forgetting to thank the Kings munificence for ſo great a dignity confer'd upon him, and proteſting that to ſhew himſelf in ſome ſort worthy thereof, he would upon all occaſions be ready to oppoſe his breaſt to the enemies Weapons. <hi>Niſſena</hi> found her ſelf touched with an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection not formerly known unto her: For though ſhe thought ſhe had loved nothing in the Prince but his worth, ſhe was then aware that ſhe likewiſe loved his preſence, not being able to imagine him in the wars, (where he might notwithſtanding exerciſe that valor which ſhe thought the onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his ſoule) without great trouble. The fatall hour of departing approached,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121609:27"/>and the Prince was already call'd upon by the Trumpets, when taking his leave of <hi>Thoas</hi> with a minde much confuſed, he went to kiſs her hand, who could not ſo much ſuppreſs the inward reſentments of her ſoul, but that they appeared viſibly by her often changing countenance. Few were the words which they ſpake to one another; but they vied whoſe eyes ſhould ſpeak moſt. <hi>Niſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> (far from her own beliefe) as ſhe turn'd her face from the Prince, ſaying, <hi>God be with you, and be ſure you return;</hi> was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to wipe the tears from off her eyes, which would have fallen in abundance, had not her wiſdome with-held them. In fine, their griefs were equall. Whilſt the Army is on its march towards <hi>Liuri,</hi> let us ſee what it was that made <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> which had formerly faithfully paid Tribute to the Crown of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> wage war againſt <hi>Thoas;</hi> and that ſome particulars may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter known, let us underſtand how the whole Iſland being ſubject to Kingly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, this onely part was then governed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocratically by the name of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
            <p>The iſſue of that famous <hi>Ptolomy</hi> vvho built thoſe foure Cities vvhich vvere called <hi>Arſinoe,</hi> being all dead, nine of the chief
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121609:28"/>Lords of <hi>Cyprus</hi> divided the Kingdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and for a while ruled by the Title of <hi>Petty Kings. Affroditius,</hi> the powerfulleſt amongſt them, occaſioned by his death, the ſubverſion of that divided <hi>Empire,</hi> vvhilſt diſpute ariſing vvhich of the reſt ſhould ſucceed to the command of that part of the Crown vvhich vvas now vacant, <hi>Byamartes,</hi> the moſt valiant, not to ſay the moſt raſh, endeavoured, and did therein ſucceed, to get the poſſeſſion thereof by force of Arms. His naturall deſire of inlarging his confines, not being herewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſatisfied, being beyond meaſure gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, and as vviſe as he needed to be, he took from five of the others their little Scepters: and the other two fortifying themſelves in the Citie of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> ſeated upon the banks of the <hi>Sirian</hi> ſea, and having received recruits of Men and Victuals from <hi>Soria,</hi> made <hi>Biamartes</hi> diſpair of over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming them by force of Arms: he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took himſelfe to plots and ſtratagems, vvhich proved all vain. Retiring from the ſiege, he ſtill ruminated how he might make himſelfe maſter of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vvhich his glory and dominion ſeemed to be imperfect and cut ſhort. He adviſed hereupon ſo long, as at laſt he pitcht upon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121609:28"/>an enterprize, vvhich by how much more dangerous it vvas, ſo much vvas the event thereof more ſucceſsfull: if out of no other reaſon, perhaps becauſe Fortune hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvayes been obſerved to be as favourable to Raſhneſs, as an enemy to Wiſdome. He choſe twelve of his moſt valiant and adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous Souldiers, and making them be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareld Country-like, ſome like ſimple foot Souldiers, ſome like mercenary Artificers, and ſome like Mechanick Plebcians; He willed them to get into <hi>Famagoſta</hi> under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall pretences, and to tarry there in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of his coming; who ſoon after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cut ſhort, and altered the colour of his haire and beard, went thither in a flovenly manner, and Shepheard-like apparell, loaded with greaſie Wooll. His intenſion was to expoſe himſelfe to all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo as he might kill thoſe two petty Kings who hindred him from intirely poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing that Kingdome, which without that Citie ſeemed to his ambition but a Body that had ſome joynt lopt off. He imagined that either he or ſome of his getting into the Courts of thoſe petty Kings, might poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly come to mingle poyſon (whereof each of them was well provided) amidſt their meats: or elſe by night to bring ſuch a
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121609:29"/>of powder into the lower Vaults of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, as might ſuffice to blow up the Walls thereof, wherewithall both to kill and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his enemies at once. If nothing elſe ſhould ſucceed, he ſhould learn the exact quantity of the people, their plenty or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury of Ammunition, the condition of their Souldiery, their inward proviſions and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifications of the Citie; and finally all ſuch occurrences as might facilitate unto him the way how to take that Citie by ſtorm, which he could not doe by ſtratagem. He determined and performed; but if he went to vanquiſh, he was vanquiſhed, though the loſs did at the laſt occaſion his Victory. His feigned condition of a Shepheard getting him acceſs without ſuſpition into all places, he made uſe therof to pry into all particulars w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> might conduce to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of his deſigns. Being one morning invited by his curioſity to ſee the inſide of a ſumptuous Palace (the great men of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> uſing in thoſe dayes freely to permit every one to enter their habitations) he ſtept into a garden, and gazing upon a ſide of the Houſe which was all made of pureſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he might ſee a Woman ſitting upon a little riſe of a Hill drying her wet black hair at the Sun beams. She ſitting a good while
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121609:29"/>ſtill, and ſeeing one look fixtly on her in a habit which made her beleeve him to be ſome ſimple Countrey Clown, who dazled with her more then uſual beauty, ſtood greedily gazing on her, broke forth into a lowd laughter, and ſaid unto him, <hi>What is't you look ſo earneſtly upon Companion? Did you never ſee a woman before? Yes La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>I have ſeen other women, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of ſo exquiſite a Beauty. Look thy belly full upon me then,</hi> ſaid ſhe; whilſt a Gentlewoman came with an Ivory Comb, to put her hair in order, <hi>Biamartes</hi> forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what perſonage he repreſented, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt by ſpeeches and behaviour befitting his true condition and mind, diſcovered himſelf to have nothing in him of Clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, but his apparell. But knowing how much it imported him to be taken for what he appeared to be, he began with divers ſenſleſs words and ſpeeches to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, masked over with ſimplicity, to move them to laughter, who had delighted a good while to make themſelves merry with him. At laſt they departed from the little riſe of the Hill, and he went out of the Palace ſo far in love with this Lady, as he found it much a harder matter to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his own thoughts, then to fight a nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Army.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121609:30"/>
            <p>'Twas a wonder that being blinded by love, he could yet ſee that he could hope for no ſucceſs, neither in his martial affairs by the death of his Enemies, nor yet in his love. Wherefore he wiſely reſolved to leave <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> where he had reaped no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the loſs of his heart, and the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving expoſed himſelf to the evident danger of his life, liberty and renown which he had won at ſuch expence of valour. He left the City, as did ſeverally thoſe that depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on him; except one of the craftieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, who by his command ſtaid to prie into the proceedings of the petty Kings, and to diſcover that Ladies condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whoſe merit had wrought upon a Kings affection. <hi>Byamartes</hi> perceived af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards how raſh his enterpriſe was: but according to the cuſtom of great ones, yea of all ſuch as have been favoured by for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, he attributed that to the goodneſs of his own wit, which was the meer gift of a friendly fortune. He ceaſed not this mean while, at a great expence of treaſure, and the full extent of his power, to raiſe all ſuch men and arms as he could, to aſſault <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta</hi> again, which being impoſſible to be beſieged on that ſide towards the ſea, was not to be taken but by aſſault. Though he
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121609:30"/>were buſied about ſo hard an enterpriſe, yet could he not forget her vvho had rob'd him of his heart, but thirſted the more to make himſelf maſter of the City. This mean vvhile he vvhom he had left in <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> having inform'd himſelf touching the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, found that ſhe vvas of a noble and rich Family, allyed to the beſt houſes of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though her husband, as having too great and numerous a retinue vvas not vvell looked upon, but rather held under by thoſe petty Kings vvho knevv their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain Dominion to be yet but vveakly grounded: vvhich made her be better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to <hi>Biamartes</hi> his Party, then to theirs. The crafty Officer thought it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his beſt courſe to let it come to her knowledge by one of her houſhold ſervants whom he had by great ſums of gold cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, that <hi>Biamartes</hi> being come into that City by ſtealth, and unknown, was falne mightily in love with her, in ſo much as he was ſent by him to offer her together with his ſoul, whatſoever his Crown was able to do, ſhe being the ſole Miſtreſs of his will. <hi>Telisbe</hi> for ſo was this Lady called thought it impoſſible that a great King ſhould have hazarded himſelf within the precincts of an Enemies Wall, and that having ſuch impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121609:31"/>affairs of War upon his hands, he could have leaſure to think of love; but did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imagin that this was a plot of ſome one or other that was in love with her, to make tryal of her chaſtitie, or elſe that it was ſome of <hi>Biamartes</hi> ſtratagems whereby to make himſelf Maſter of that City, which was only wanting to compleat his Dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all <hi>Cyprus.</hi> Were it then that ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know whether ſhe were grown ſo ingenuous or no as to diſcover the plots of others, or that eg'd on by the itch of ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhe would gladly know the certainty, whether her beauty were ſuch or no, as to have operation in the heart of a great Prince and valliant Warrler ſhe would be punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally inform'd by this her domeſtick ſervant, who it was that had prevailed ſo far with her as to make her venter upon ſo raſh a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. She wrought ſo much by intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and by threats, as ſhe learn'd all ſhe knew out of her: Which was no more but that dazled by the brightneſs of the gold whereof a ſtranger had been very liberal unto her, ſhe was induced to deliver ſuch meſſages, believing ſhe ſhould not find her eaſie to conſent, but yet ready enough to pardon the folly of a fault which had got her ſo much wealth. The Lady ſeemed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121609:31"/>to be appeas'd, and asked her whether ſhe thought the ſtranger would be perſwaded to ſpeak with her her ſelf or no, charging her that when he ſhould come to receive his anſwer, ſhe ſhould deſire him to do ſo. The good woman promiſed total obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet was ſhe afraid and doubtful, leaſt this might be done out of cunning, that her Lady might come to know him, and ſo cauſe him to receive deſerv'd puniſhment: yet confirm'd by her Ladies redoubled Oaths, who proteſted to her that it procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only out of a certain itch of curioſity, and knowing her ingenuous and ſweet na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhe reſolved to let the ſtranger know, that her Miſtreſs was not only ready, but very deſirous to ſpeak with him. He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made fearfull by too much facility, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that whenſoever it might be ſo done as he might be ſure to come by no harm, he would be very ready to receive ſo great an honour: not that he did believe there could be any abuſe uſed, or traps laid by ſuch a Lady, but that the favour ſeemed to him to be too ſudden, and too exceeding great: which anſwer being by her brought back unto her inquiſitive Lady, after a long conſultation had, they reſolved (ſo great a power in Women hath curioſity and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121609:32"/>that before he ſhould come to Parley with her, a little tender child, whom he very well knew to be <hi>Telisbes</hi> only ſon, ſhould be delivered into his cuſtody. By this her ſo great expreſſion of fidelity, he infer'd ſafety to himſelf from all deceit, ſo as he refuſed all other ſecurity ſave what might proceed from her curteous Ingenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The manner, and hour of their inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locution was agreed upon, wherein to <hi>Bia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martes</hi> good luck it was proved true, that the ſame Fortune which ſparingly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds her favours from ſome, diſpenſeth them prodigally to other ſome. With ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy worthy of one who laid open the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous paſſions of a King, the crafty and eloquent Officer endeavoured to perſwade <hi>Telisbe,</hi> that ſhe was more dearly beloved by <hi>Biamartes</hi> then any thing that did never ſo nearly concern his Crown, nay more then his own ſoul. She at that inſtant, were it either out of decency, or that her ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and curioſity being already ſatisfied, ſome new thoughts came in her head, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: <hi>Friend! if I had imagined that your diſcourſe ſhould have tended to theſe vain expresſions of Love, whether they be true or falſe, I ſhould as well have refuſed you audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as I ſhal alwaies refuſe to make my heart
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121609:32"/>a receptaecle of any other affections, then what prompted by my Genius and dutie I have dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated as inviolable and eternal to my Lord and husband. I was perſwaded to give you hearing, out of a belief that</hi> Biamartes <hi>in love with ſomewhat elſe then my beautie, would by theſe his pretences of love, ſeek to diſcover how my houſe is inclined to theſe our unjuſt pettie Princes, who carrie themſelves unwiſely and very violently againſt all thoſe of my bloud. If he will that I do faithfully asſiſt him in his Victories, I am at his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal; for though a woman, I will make all other Princes learn by the example of theſe, how to treat their Nobilitie better: but if his only pretence be to diſhonour me, he does but loſe his labour, for a nobly born ſoul doth alwaies more eſteem honour then life.</hi> Not without won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and much joy did the other hear theſe expreſſions, and ſeeing ſo large a way o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to undream'd of good ſucceſs, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered: <hi>That he was certain, as much as his Maſter would be diſpleaſed to hear his love repulſed by her, ſo much would he be pleaſed to underſtand the offer of her adherence to him in the winning of that City; that he ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired her to give him leave to acquaint</hi> Byamartes <hi>with her favourable intentions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him: that then he would return with
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121609:33"/>freer reſolves; aſſuring her that ſhe ſhould not befriend a Prince who would repay her with ingratitude.</hi> He without further delay, went from <hi>Famagoſta</hi> ſafely and eaſily under a counterfeit habit; commerce being allow'd to all men, nor entrance denyed to any on who came in alone, unarm'd, and who would go out at convenient and ſet hours. He came to <hi>Biamartes,</hi> who being already Maſter of the Field, was levying of more men, and was incamped not above twelve miles from the Town, to whom having related what he had learn'd of new, <hi>Byamar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> inſtantly forgot <hi>Telisbes</hi> beauty; and the poor childe Love, wholly compos'd of tenderneſs and ſwavitie, fled from his heart, and gave place for <hi>Mars</hi> to enter, who in a terrible and bloudy manner did in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment uſurp the ſeat. He grew impatient to ſee himſelf wholly Victorious over his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: ſo as ſending back the Meſſenger in haſte with order to promiſe <hi>Telisbe</hi> in his behalf whatſoever ſhe could deſire in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; were it even the fee Farm of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> with the Title of Government, ſo as ſhe would deviſe a means how he might ſurpriſe it. This Meſſenger at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn found the Lady more roſolv'd to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt <hi>Byamartes</hi> now then ever, ſince concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121609:33"/>his love addreſſes, ſhe had told her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band how the King had craftily indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to draw from her, to what ſide he, as head of a numerous faction, did adhere; and that if he would be pleaſed to ſecond that fortune which offered its forelock to him; the means was in readineſs whereby he might take revenge for all his ill uſage received from the petty Princes. He was a little jealous to hear his Wife talke thus, though afterwards wieghing every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, having adviſed with himſelf, and ſome of his neareſt friends, he reſolved not to let ſlip ſo fair an oportunity of revenge, and of advancing his own greatneſs and Fortune. <hi>Telisbe</hi> would ſpeak no more with <hi>Biamartes</hi> officer without her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands being preſent, and all things being agreed upon between them, he returned to the Camp inſtructed in all that was to be done in execution of the enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Telisbe</hi> deſired, and did obtain it, that when <hi>Byamartes</hi> ſhould have made himſelf maſter of the Citie, he ſhould give way, that for the future it ſhould be governed by the Nobles, and by the name of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; but ſtill as feudatory and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary to his Majeſty in a great ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, whoſe Vicegerent ſhould in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121609:34"/>hold the principall place, though his Authority ſhould not exceed that of the other Senators. For what remain'd, that the Army ſhould draw nigh, and ſhould give an aſſault by night, for that by ſuch helps as he ſhould meet withall, he ſhould with eaſe, and without the expence of bloud obtain the Victory. All things were agreed upon, and ſo ſucceſsfully executed, as one of the petty Princes was ſlain whilſt he fought valiantly in the defence of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace by night, and the other flying away by Sea, truſted his ſafety with the Winds, paſſing in a little Bark to the banks of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> From that time till <hi>Thoas</hi> his reign, <hi>Famagoſta</hi> was peacefully governed in the form of a Republick; when rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he diſpatcht away Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo</hi> to chaſtiſe ſo raſh and inſolent a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion. The hidden and wicked Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of one of <hi>Thoas</hi> his chief Miniſters of ſtate, had excited, nay neceſſitated that ſtate to the violent reſolution of taking up Arms againſt its Lord and Maſter. Who this wicked one was, and to what miſchievous ends he complotted theſe revolutions, we ſhall ſhortly know, together with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fatall ſucceſſes. Let it ſuffice for the preſent to know, That an Order from his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121609:34"/>Majeſty authenticated and ſealed by his Kingly Seal, was read in full Senat by the Kings Vicegerent in <hi>Famagoſta;</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reply or intermiſſion of time, to boot with the ordinary Tribute, four thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Talents ſhould be by them disburſt towards the occurrent affairs. Thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were aſtoniſhed to hear of ſo unaccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed &amp; burthenſom a demand, there not being moneys enough neither in the publick Exchequers, nor yet in mens privat purſes, to make up ſo great a payment; they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a prorogation of the Vicegerent, prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting howſoever that they were altogether unable to ſatisfie his Majeſties deſires. They were anſwered, that they were ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to reſolve, and to take into their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations the particulars expreſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Order, without further re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply or loſs of time.</p>
            <p>The poor Senators knew not what to ſay; in all meetings both publick and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat, the Kings indiſcretion was the ſole ſubject of diſcourſe, when many of them received privat advertiſements by Letters, that <hi>Thoas</hi> taking a <hi>Caprichio</hi> to annull the Republick, had made uſe of a pretence of exacting a Contribution from them, which was impoſſible for them to pay.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121609:35"/>That if they ſhould make ready payment of what was demanded, either in part or in whole, he was reſolved to make uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to wage war with them at their own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence; That if they did not execute his Order, he would declare them to be diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient, and proclaim them Rebels, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the Crown. That the very Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> aſham'd &amp; ſcandaliz'd at the apparent injuſtice, deſir'd that ſo famous &amp; ancient a Common wealth ſhould now make ſome glorious reſentment againſt that King, who having loſt his reaſon in his love to a baſe Woman, had already crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her Queen, to the end that the people might be governed by a mungrell ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an ignoble ſtock mixt with the Royal Bloud. That the onely remedy they had to prevent their imminent ruine, was to put on a noble reſolution of preventing him ſpeedily with Arms. That they would not want aſſiſtants and part-takers even in the very Court it ſelf. Thoſe of <hi>Famagoſta</hi> provoked by ſo violent incitements, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to prevent <hi>Thoas,</hi> by ſetting on his ſtate on the ſide of <hi>Siuri;</hi> and though they were provided but with a few Soldiers, they lead them into the Field, not ceaſing this mean while to raiſe men with all their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121609:35"/>might: And to this purpoſe they diſpatcht away Commiſſaries into <hi>Soria,</hi> from the King whereof they promis'd themſelves up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions aſſiſtance and ſuccour.</p>
            <p>They ſoon heard how that Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo</hi> was marching towards them with a numerous Army: When the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the <hi>Famagoſtan</hi> Troops, who being diſperſt abroad, ſack the Countrey every where, to the terror and loſs of the poore Countrey people, ſummon'd them all back into the two Towns which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taken, &amp; fortifying themſelves there with cutting deep Ditches and Trenches, they waited for the enemy, whilſt the Militia of the Citie was drawn forth, and Forces were raiſed in divers parts, that they might afterwards appeare in the field ready to fight. <hi>Thoas</hi> his Army incampt it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Town of <hi>Siuri,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Pigadia;</hi> and all the neighbouring places being by the provident Prince provided with Garriſons, he ſent forth ſix Troops of Horſe, &amp; ten Companies of Foot, giving them order to uſe all means poſſible where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might draw the Enemies out of thoſe Towns wherein they had fortified themſelves. This was not eaſily to be done; For after a long reſiſtance made by
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121609:36"/>them of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> they received ſuccours, ſo that it behoved <hi>Doralbo's</hi> forces to fight, which though they did with little loſs of men, yet loſt they much reputation, failing in their firſt enterpriſe. True it is that the <hi>Famagostians</hi> growing hereupon bold, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied out with a great many men, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too far advanc'd in purſuit of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Horſe, who did of purpoſe leaſurely retreat, they found the way ſhut up as they returned, ſo as intercepted in the midſt, the greateſt part of them were taken priſoners, or cut in pieces; ſome of them who had the fortune to eſcape, withdrawing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a neighbouring Wood.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Nicoſia</hi> this mean while the ſick King grew daily worſe and worſe, ſo as his Caſe was thought deſperate, ſo much the rather for that being grown exceeding weak, the Phyſick which was preſcribed, either wrought not at all, or wrought contrary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects to the ends it was given. In fine, he muſt die, and in ſtead of going into a nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Bed to rejoyce within the Arms of his Beloved, he muſt be put into a doleful Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin, and laid in the boſome of Death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Unfortunate Thoas, I wiſh at leaſt the Heavens had never ſuffered thee to have ſeen</hi> Niſſena, <hi>thou then wouldſt not in departing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121609:36"/>from this world, have known the ſorrow of parting from her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Knowing himſelfe neer the unavoidable paſſage of Death, he called in to the help of his oppreſſed heart, that native generoſity which in his life had never forſaken him, and with a deep ſigh, wherewith he ſeemed to baniſh all fear, he with a cheerful coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance wherein undauntedneſſe might be diſcerned, commanded that <hi>Niſſena</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the chiefe Lords and Barons of the Court ſhould be ſent for to him. The ſorrowfull Queen being come, ſhe ſate her down by the Kings bed ſide, and taking be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her faireſt hands, the fading and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing left hand of her dying Husband, ſhe ſaid unto him, <hi>Oh Sir, How doe you feel your ſelfe? Well,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Now that I have all my content by me; but I muſt die, I muſt die, O</hi> Niſſena, <hi>neither do I grieve thereat, for I know I was born mortall; but onely becauſe I am to leave you, and to leave you before you be wholly mine.</hi> At the hearing of words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt with ſuch tender affection, tears in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance began to fall from the eyes of the afflicted Lady, which at the arrival of the Court Lords, ſhe with much adoe detained. The Lords and Rulers of the Kingdome entred the diſmall Chamber with ſilent
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121609:37"/>reverence; and many of them being by this time got together, and ſtanding bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed before the Bed, the King comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them all to ſit down. Here, a melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly and ſhort Preludium being made by an univerſal ſilence to the Kings diſcourſe, he with a fainting voyce having firſt loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them all in the face, feebly ſpoke thus: At laſt, my Friends, or rather my dear Children, after ſo many years wherein I have upheld the Crown of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> I am come to pay my laſt duty to Nature by Death. I die, and die contented, knowing that I have never upon any occaſion been wanting to any one either in juſtice or in clemency; I have always loved my ſubjects more tenderly then my ſelf or mine own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts; and I call your ſelves and heaven to witneſs whether I had ever any other end, then to govern like a good Shepheard, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſhed my ſweat, nay my very bloud for the good of my Flock. It may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be, that without any conſent of my will, ſome one may think himſelf ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ill dealt withall through my rigor, or injur'd by ſome innocent fault of mine. If I have done amiſs, I have done it out of ignorance, and for doing it, I firſt humbly ask pardon of Gods hands, then at your
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121609:37"/>hands who are here preſent, and laſtly from the meaneſt and pooreſt of my Vaſſals. It hath pleaſed the Gods, peradventure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I knew not how to deſerve it, that I die void of ſucceſſion, or an heir, to whom leaving that love hereditary which I bear to you, I might aſſure my ſelf that for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture you were to be govern'd with thoſe juſt ends wherewith I have always governed you: But my faults have been too great to others, which have withheld me from having deſerved ſo greatly a deſired felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and death would be too welcome to me, if I could die with this content. Yeild I beſeech you unto my will, and be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall wel pleaſed; and if the Love and Juſtice which I have ever indifferently born unto you all, have merited any retribution from you, I beg a comfort of you able to make me happie before I breath my laſt. Grant it unto your King, if you wil not that he die, ſlain rather by deſperation then by ſickneſs. Grant it I deſire you, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, I conjure you, if for nothing elſe, for the publick proſperity which is to ariſe from thence: I would have my Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to paſs from me to <hi>Niſſena:</hi> I know that as being the laſt of my race, I may by the ancient Laws of this Kingdom juſtly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121609:38"/>of; but I will receive that as a gift from your conſent, which I might free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſe of according to mine own will. Let her afterwards chuſe a husband, whom I wiſh may be ſuch a companion to her, both in the Kingdom and in her bed, as you by her privat election may enjoy publique tranquility. Howſoever, if it had pleaſed the Gods to bleſs me with longer life, ſhe muſt have been your Queen; ſhe is already Crown'd; The Fates have given you her for your Queen, and the Gods, knowing that ſhe deſerves a Kingdom, and that a Kingdom is but an <hi>adequat</hi> reward to her deſerts. I vow unto you by that ſincere Faith which may be expected from a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man, ſhe is no leſs inwardly then out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly beautiful. Did I not know her to be ſo, I would not propound her as a Head to thoſe my dear Subjects, whoſe happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I ſhal for ever love, even in my grave. Let the performance of this my pleaſure be your charge <hi>Mintaurus,</hi> who are my chief Preſident; for methinks I ſee a willing content in every ones countenance that <hi>Niſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſena</hi> ſhould be their Queen. <hi>Mintaurus</hi> riſing from his ſeat, kneeled down and ſaid, If the heavens have ordained (which the Gods forbid) that your Majeſtie forgoe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121609:38"/>this life, the Queen ſhal ſee how highly her merits ſhal be obſerved by me, and how obſequiouſly your Majeſties commands ſhal be obeyed. They all one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kneeled down before her, and humbly kiſſed the hem of her garment, to which the much grieved Ladie anſwered only in tears which falling in abundance from her eyes, invited many of the ſtanders by to do the like. Do not bewail (ſaid the dying King with an almoſt ſmiling eye) the loſs of a King, ſince you make ſo advantageous a change in ſo worthie a Queen. I wil carrie with me the memory of your goodneſſe my faithful Subjects, into <hi>Eliſium;</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you your <hi>Thoas</hi> who dies. Here, his voice growing very weak, he made ſignes that all ſhould withdraw except <hi>Niſſena;</hi> to whom with words hardly brought forth for want of breath, he expreſſed his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſcarcely underſtood. I die <hi>Niſſena;</hi> whilſt I lived, as ſoon as I had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to know you, I made you a free gift of my heart; in death, ſince I have nothing to preſent you withall more worthie of you, I give you the Scepter of <hi>Cyprus;</hi> after death, my Soul ſhal eternally love you. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Niſ</hi> — and not being able to pronounce her whole name, he at once loſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121609:39"/>both his memorie and his voice, which he never recovered again. Help, help, cried the Queen aloud, help my Lord the King, for he dies; and weeping downright; ſhe fel in a ſwound upon the beds ſide, which ſeemed a hears loaded with two dead corps. Phiſitians and ſervants came running in, and women being ſent for, the ſwounding Ladie was carried to her Lodgings, whilſt with divers Balſoms, Cordials, and odo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riferous extractions they indeavoured, but in vain, to recall the King to his ſences. He laie languiſhing all that night, til the break of day, and then breathed out his ſoul.</p>
            <p>Alas that neither Kings, nor yet King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms are exempt from the darts of death, and in death greatneſs and Dignities ſerve only to make death the more grievous. Behold that Court which but awhile afore abounded in Feaſting and Nuptial Jolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, now become a Theatre of ſorrow, plentiful only in dolorous tears, and ſhal ſhortly be the Scene of Fatal and Tragical revolutions. The Queen, when ſhe was come to her ſelf, wondred to find her ſelf not near the bed of her expiring husband, after whoſe condition ſhe immediately en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, whether he was yet alive or no, or whether he had for ever abandoned her:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121609:39"/>Anſwer was made that he was at reſt, and that ſhe ſhould do wel to mind her ſelf, for he wanted for no care nor poſſible aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Early the next morning papers were found thrown about in divers parts of the Palace, wherein was publiſht that the King was dead by ſlowly working poiſon; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied by ſome who plotted yet more exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable aſſaſſinations to the univerſal ruine of the whole Kingdom. This was whiſpered up and down the Court til at laſt it came to <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s ears, who betaking her ſelf to freſh ſorrows, would have accompanied her Husband in death. She paſt afterwards from tears to ſo impetuous and blind a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of revenge, as ſhe ſeemed out of her wits; threatning the Gallows, Ax, Fire, ruine and deſtruction to whoſoever had kild <hi>Thoas</hi> But there was not the leaſt ſigne, nor imagination to be had who this wicked one ſhould be. <hi>Mintaurus</hi> came in, vvho under pretence of obviating thoſe ſcandalous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which might be occaſioned by the Queens ill regulated violence, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and redoubled the Guard, comforting her in an almoſt imperious and ſevere man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Not long after his ſon <hi>Melaſpus</hi> came in to comply with her, and to offer her not only what he ow'd unto her as a Subject,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121609:40"/>and ſervant, but promiſing with his ſword and the expence of his bloud to do what in him lay, to bring her conſolation by way of revenge. Theſe unuſual complements, misbecoming his rough and beſtial nature were obſerv'd by <hi>Eurania, Niſſena</hi>'s Ant, but not by her, who quite loſt in the paſſions of grief and revenge, minded nothing but her own fury and affliction. The Kings Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals were by <hi>Mintaurus</hi> orders celebrated with no extraordinarie Pomp, upon whom by reaſon of his dignitie the Government and intereſt of the Kingdom depending, he indeavor'd by unuſual kindneſſes to win into the good opinion of the great ones, and by liberalitys, never by him before practiſ'd, to to make the ſoldiery &amp; the common people his friends: he notwithſtanding made many to be impriſon'd, and amongſt others one of the late Kings ſecretarys, pretending that they were complices in the murder of one of the chief Gentlemen of <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> who was ſlain ſome daies before. He acquainted the Queen with all proceedings, whoſe grief not being yet over, committed all affairs and expeditions to his charge. This was the only thing which he gaped after; who deſires to ſtrengthen his own authoritie with the people, and to weaken the Queens
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121609:40"/>power, haſted apace towards the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of his vaſt and proud deſignes. <hi>Melaſpus</hi> ceaſed not to wait often upon <hi>Niſſena,</hi> indeavouring by his obſequiouſneſs and ſervice to work himſelf into her good opinion, as being in love, I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more with her, or with the Kingdom. This his new waie of proceeding was known by al men to be but craft which aim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Crovvn, and made him more hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the eies of many, then had his dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable conditions done before. The Court was ſufficiently aware to what end <hi>Mintau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> actions tended, as alſo thoſe of <hi>Melaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> and both <hi>Eurania</hi> and <hi>Niſſena</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it too, though too late; who finding her Guards to be changed, how ſhe was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by none but <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his friends and kindred, and even deprived of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of her moſt intruſted waiting women, knew ſhe had almoſt totally loſt her Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power, or was rather of a Queen become a ſervant; whilſt every vvhere, and in all things <hi>Mintaurus</hi> vvas more obeyed then ſhe. She deſired that a Councel of State might be called, but it vvas deferr'd under pretence of his indiſpoſition of health, and of the abſence of many of the chief Lords, vvho after the Kings death had vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dravvn
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121609:41"/>themſelves not only from the Court, but from the Citie. She deſired to be inform'd of many Occurrences of the Kingdom; more particularly of the War of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> and vvhat had ſucceeded ſince the Prince <hi>Doralbo's</hi> expedition: But ſhe could learn nothing but Ambiguities and falſhoods. In fine ſhe found her ſelf utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loſt, not having any one left her vvith vvhom to adviſe, and make knovvn her mind ſave only <hi>Eurania,</hi> vvho amongſt the reſt of her vexing cares, ſhe acquainted vvith her amorous inclination vvhich ſince the Kings death, did much increaſe in her tovvards <hi>Doralbo. Melaſpus</hi> this mean while, who by his Fathers perſvvaſions, did often viſit <hi>Nisſena,</hi> could no longer hold commerce with thoſe fair eyes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out becoming in reality her very fervent Lover; and forgetting his Fathers ſordid and avaritious ends, which aimed at the unjuſt poſſeſſing of the Kingnom, he aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to nothing elſe but the poſſeſſion of <hi>Nisſena's</hi> beauty. 'Tis a folly to expoſe ones ſelf to the flames, with a thought of not remaining if not burnt, at leaſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly warmed. <hi>Nisſena</hi> was at all times ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding handſome, but being atired in Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovvs aparrel and vails, ſhe appeared to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do her ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121609:41"/>
            <p>It was no wonder therefore if <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> vvho vvas vvont formerly onely to follow after vvanton and laſcivious love, ſuffered himſelfe at this time to be taken by that countenance, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> though it breathed forth nothing but noble flames, did notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding raviſh with a redoubled violence, he therefore ſollicited his father to ſuch reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as might give him <hi>Niſſena</hi> in poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo as his ſons intreaties joyned to the conatural goads of Ambition &amp; Avarice, <hi>Mintaurus</hi> reſolv'd himſelf to propound <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſpus</hi> to <hi>Niſſena</hi> for Husband. She bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but wiſely keeping in the height of her diſdain, took time to give anſwer, ſo as the vvary vvicked fellow perceiv'd ſhe was not much inclin'd to ſuch a marriage; And though he feigned, yet inwardly inraged, he ſaid within himſelfe, <hi>Thou ſhalt either marry Melaſpus, or have Death for thy Bridegroom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen ſaw her ſelf afterwards worſe treated then ever, and the ill uſage practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hitherto by <hi>Mintaurus</hi> with hidden Art, began to degenerate into evident neglects. She was no more acquainted, as formerly, with the affairs of the Kingdome, nor for all that ſhe could do, could ſhe ever get the Councell to meet. She was attended as meanly as might be, onely in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121609:42"/>neceſſity, not as became her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; the number of her Courtiers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in her waiting rooms being every day decreaſed, and the number of Souldiers every day increaſed. <hi>Melaſpus</hi> only, whoſe flames grew daily greater, continued to ſerve her, though the little correſpondency or gratitnde that he met withal, might have made him ſee he was not at all reſpected. The Niece and Aunt perplext between theſe ſtraits, reſolved it not onely needful for them, but neceſſary to acquaint <hi>Doralbo</hi> by Letters, how barbarouſly they were treated by <hi>Mintaurus</hi> after the Kings death: And this <hi>Niſſena</hi> was the willinger induced unto, now that ſhe ſaw the way open unto her to make with honour her affection known to that gallant Prince, whoſe love ſhe now e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd a greater fortune then the Crown. 'I was hard for them to get the letter ſafely conveyd unto him; but wary <hi>Eurania</hi> ſent it by a very truſty Meſſenger. For what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd they reſolved to ſhew themſelves for the future more inclin'd to the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Niſſena's</hi> marriage with <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> whoſe affection ſhould be fed and nouriſht by her with ſome ſeeming content: yet ſo cunningly, as a ſudden change might not cauſe ſuſpition. The ſad couple were toſſed
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121609:42"/>between the billows of theſe anxious thoughts, and <hi>Niſſena</hi> oppreſt with unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Melancholy, was more afflicted then uſually, when a young man appear'd before her of a noble enough aſpect, though not very richly attir'd, who having bowed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently unto her, ſpake to her in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, The weight of affairs vvherein your Majeſties life and the poſſeſſion of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are concern'd, required that I ſhould come before your preſence: and for that I was often denied entrance by the guard, I who am a Merchants ſon of this Citie, have abuſed the Souldiers, making them believe that I was ſent for by you, with direction to bring you ſome Looking-glaſſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the better to colour over the Fiction, I have brought good ſtore with me; and to that purpoſe, Madam, I will preſent you with a Glaſſe, wherein you ſhal ſee the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked practiſes of others, and the imminent dangers which hang over you. Be not, I beſeech you, offended, that Fortune hath made choyce of me your unworthy ſervant, and moſt humble ſubject, as an inſtrument to withdraw you from thoſe misfortunes to which you are ſo much the more expos'd, for that you doe the leſſe diſcern them; as long as my Relation ſhal ſerve to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121609:43"/>you need not care who I am. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a moneth ſince I was impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by order from the Preſident <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurus,</hi> onely for being caſually in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in the night ſeaſon with ſome ſuch young men as my ſelfe; amongſt whom there aroſe ſome diſpute about love-affairs: &amp; was ready to be ſet at liberty when by the unadviſed Keeper, a Secretary of my lare Soveraign was brought into the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon where I was. He wondred to ſee me there, the Jaylor having received expreſs command, as the Secretary told me, to put him into ſome priſon where no body was. The ſecretary inquiring the misfortune that had brought me thither, I anſwered, 'Twas for a buſineſſe of ſmall concern, and that I hoped that very day to be ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. He rejoyced with me at my good fortune, adding, I would it might pleaſe the Gods, that according to my innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy I might likewiſe be ſet free; but I feare I ſhall by the loſſe of my life pay for the puniſhment which is due to the wickedneſs of other men. I think it notwithſtanding a great good fortune to have met you here, my friend, for you are to be a means of free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faireſt and moſt deſerving Queen of the world from thoſe dangers ſhe is likely
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121609:43"/>to undergoe. Know that <hi>Mintaurus,</hi> the wickedeſt of as many men as live, grown inſolent by that good fortune which to boot with making him rich, and having brought him into favour with the King, hath raiſed him to the degree of chief Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, ſeeing the King without iſſue, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ambitious of the Crown, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to open a way to his enjoying it by the moſt cruell and unjuſt means that ever was deviſed by any Fiend in Hell. When <hi>Thoas</hi> was reſolved to marry <hi>Niſſena,</hi> he ſaw the ground-work of his barbarous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions began to ſhake, and therefore cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſlow working poyſon to be mingled in the Kings meat, which by a lingring ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath brought him to his grave. 'Twas he who by a blind letter indeavoured to make <hi>Niſſena</hi> run away, or at leaſt to raiſe jealouſies in her, and make ſome miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings between her and the King, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſt when <hi>Thoas</hi> ſhould die, he might leave the Scepter hereditary to her. He was the wicked one, who ſending falſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for grievous contributions to the Common wealth of <hi>Famagosta,</hi> and uſing other wicked Art, made them take up arms againſt the King, to the end that all the Souldiers being drawn out of <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> his
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121609:44"/>machinations might be the eaſilier compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. He is that wicked one who to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat all his unjuſt Acts, will have <hi>Niſsena</hi> to marry his ſon <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> or elſe will poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon her, or put her to ſome more cruell death. And when he ſhall have made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of the Kingdome, I am ſure the people wil be made to weep tears of bloud, they ſhall be oppreſt, not governed; tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized over, not ruled: He finally, leſt I might in time ſmell out his Treacheries, hath commanded that I ſhould be buried in this priſon, &amp; would have ere this have put me to death, had he known that I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of his miſdeeds. What is to become of me, and of a many more that are impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with me, is beſt known to thoſe ſtars which ſometimes powre down greater ſhowres of Misfortune upon the innocent then on the guilty. When you ſhall be ſet at liberty, delay not I beſeech you, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover all his frauds unto the Queen, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her either to flie from the Tyrants hands, or to incite the people to revenge, &amp; to work his ruine, and tell her from me that though <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his friends appear nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and potent, he is notwithſtanding ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by all the people, and to all ſuch of the Nobility as are not allied to him. The
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121609:44"/>Souldiers are grown to ſide with him, by reaſon of his profuſe liberality towards them; but they are but a few, the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being much weakened; and the very Guards of the Gallies and of the Court, by reaſon of the expedition againſt <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is all I can ſerve her in; as for wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and counſell, ſhe is of herſelfe ſo well provided, as I hope (and may the Gods make my hopes prove true) to ſee her freed from ſo many imminent dangers, and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over the ruines of her enemie. He was about to have told me how he came to know theſe <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his wickedneſſes, and had already begun to ſay ſomewhat of his love-affairs, when the Keeper came to invite me to my deſired liberty. I came forth, thinking thoſe benigne influences which had whilſt I was in priſon, afforded me the moſt happy occaſion of ſerving your Majeſty. And then bowing low before her feet, he added; Yet I cannot but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile that fortune which imbitters all my content, by making me the bringer of ſuch fatal news of imminent dangers. The yong man ceaſed ſpeaking, and <hi>Niſſena,</hi> who not knowing what to think, had this mean while changed her countenance 100 times,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121609:45"/>fetching a deep ſigh, anſwered thus, <hi>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not for the preſent, young man, pay you with any thing but thanks for what you have told me: If it be the pleaſure of the Gods that I eſcape theſe dangers which unjuſt</hi> Mintaurus <hi>hath plotted againſt me, I will be mindfull of you, and of the trouble you have undergone to ſerve me. I could wiſh you would let me ſee you ſomtimes, leſt I may merit the title of</hi> Ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; <hi>if I ſhal fall under his treacheries, do you comiſerate my misfortunes who know my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and be, if not a publick yet a privat te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of his wickedneſs, whilſt I aſſure you, that in ſerving me, you have not ſown in the ſand; and let this ſuffice, that if I live I will teſtifie my acknowledgement otherwiſe then in words.</hi> He took his leave, and ſhe was ſo lively impreſt with what ſhe had heard, as ſhe was not wanting to herſelf in providing for her imminent dangers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doralbo</hi> had this mean while received the Letter from his beloved <hi>Niſſena,</hi> and was thereby made at once both happie, and much afflicted. Happie, for that the ſole characters of that fair hand, were able to have recall'd him to life again, had he bin already dead: Afflicted to hear of thoſe wicked demeanors which the baſe Preſident had uſed towards her, whom he reverenced
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121609:45"/>as worthy of Incenſe. He was glad that ſhe was ſucceeded to the Kingdom by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and that being aſſumed to ſo high a degree, ſhe would deigne to confide in him, and give him ſome little inckling of her correſpondencie in affection: but he was grieved that he was not preſent to hazard his life in her defence and for her ſervice. He would have preſently been gon, nay he would have flown towards <hi>Nicoſia;</hi> but he could not do ſo, becauſe the next day he was to fight the Enemy in a pitcht Field, whereupon the Victorie of that War depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and wherein the intereſt and glorie of his Queen did conſiſt. Amidſt the variety of theſe thoughts, he reſolved firſt to trie the fortune of the day: and finding his heart invigored by the graces of his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he thought himſelf already Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and joyd that he ſhould ſhortly enjoy the triumphs of his Victorie under the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious arches of thoſe eies which he adored. That night appeared an age to him, he got two hours before day out of bed; and by his command the Trumpets were ſoon heard in all his quarters, awakening thoſe who were yet aſleep, and inviting them to prepare for the battel. Arm'd all in black, he curb'd in a horſe which under a mantle of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121609:46"/>ſnow covered a fierie ſoul, haſting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to one place, ſometimes to another, to incourage his Soldiers, to give out Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the Commanders, to excite the backward, to ſuppreſs the inſolent, and to diſpoſe of all things which might make his Victorie the more eaſie, in an open plain and ſpacious field, ſave only that on the left hand there ſtood a little hill; he order'd his Army, giving the right wing to <hi>Filar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi> and the left to <hi>Theocaſtro,</hi> he himſelf kept in the midſt at the head of a choice Troop of commanded horſemen, he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran all others no leſs in valour and courage then with his ſteed, when he underſtood by ſome Scouts who he had ſent before to watch the Enemies proceedings, that the Enemie was come within a mile and a half, and already the noiſe of their Trumpets might be heard, the ſound of Drums, the neighing of Warlick horſes, and a thick cloud of duſt might be perceived to be raiſed in the air. In the <hi>Famagoſtan</hi> Army, the unexperience of the Countrie Soldiers, which were not very many, was ſupplied by the practice and valour of many Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers who were come thither in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from the adjacent ſhores and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Iſlands, called in by the renowned
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121609:46"/>name of <hi>Agenor</hi> of <hi>Soria,</hi> on whom the place of Generaliſſimo was by the Senat confer'd at a very profuſe charge: He had diſpoſed of his ſquadrons according to the <hi>Perſian</hi> manner, in whoſe Wars he had a long time been trained up, fighting gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſometimes in the condition of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat Soldier, ſometimes of a powerful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander. 1500 bow-men on horſeback marched before the body of the Army, and he himſelf followed immediately after up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a horſe whoſe bards and crupper were made of Panther skins, lined with purple and interwoven with gold; he had upon him a Jacket of azure ſatin, trim'd with long buttons of great pearl, and his head was odly wound about with Skarfs variouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coloured, beſtuck with feathers of great eſteem and price; he was provided with no other arms but only a Scimiter hanging at his left ſide, and a battel ax at his ſaddle bow: Aſſoon as the Armies were come within bow-ſhot, the Archers like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning let fly all their arrows, and dividing themſelves inſtantly into two wings, they retreated orderly, leaving the reſt of their Army open to the Enemies eie; few that were then wounded did immediately die, but not any one were his hurt never ſo
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121609:47"/>ſmall, outlived the ſpace of three days, the heads of their arrows being all dipt in dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poiſon. <hi>Doralbo</hi> and <hi>Agenor</hi> were the firſt who advanced one towards another, but imitated, and followed by great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Cavalrie, they could not come to fight hand to hand, being hindred by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther combatants who with like generoſity and fortune on both ſides, ſometimes char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on, ſometimes retreated, ſometime drove back their Enemies, who rallying again, returned to face and fight the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe party. Many fell down wounded on both ſides, troden under foot, dying, and buried before they were dead, by the confuſed number of horſes born to the ground, of broken weapons, and a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of dead bodies: <hi>Agenors</hi> horſe was ſlain under him, and had he been leſs valiant, he had in this very firſt encounter either bin ſlain or taken priſoner by the <hi>Nicoſians:</hi> but he ſlew ſo many with his Scimeter, and threw ſo many to the ground, as being in time ſuccour'd by his men, he eſcaped the evident danger of loſing either his life or li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. <hi>Doralbo</hi> received a ſlight wound in one of his arms, and doubting leaſt his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers might be diſcouraged by ſeeing him bleed, he cried out aloud; <hi>Courage my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121609:47"/>for the Victorie leans already to our ſide, and though I have often indeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either to overcome or to die, I have hitherto met with no other harm, ſave only ſo ſlight a wound, as hath hardly drawn three drops of bloud from me:</hi> Whilſt he was ſpeaking thus, he was advertiſed by a thundring ſalute of muſquet ſhot, that <hi>Filarbo</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven battel on the left ſide, and that he had had bad fortune at the very firſt; for the ranks of his pikemen who defended the muſquetiers, being broken by the Enemies launces, he might ſee them all routed, and little better then running away. He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſpeedie half turn indeavoured with many other horſmen to make reſiſtance, but was neceſſitated to face about againſt ſome other horſe which charged him on the flank, which had he not done, they were likely not only to have diſordered, but to have routed the whole Army; not at all diſcouraged herewith, he diſpatcht away a Serjant Major upon a very fleet horſe, to advertiſe <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> that with what force and fury he poſſibly could, he ſhould with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay charge the Enemies forces on his ſide, if he would not have the day loſt: He obeyed ſo luckily, as bearing down the firſt files at his fierce aſſault, who were all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121609:48"/>Soldiers, they began by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to retreat, and by and by to run down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right away; in ſo much that <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> with many of his men charged ſo home as he took the chief Standard, and meeting with none to withſtand him, he came in to the ſuccour of his brother <hi>Filarbo,</hi> who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards valliantly fighting together with him, beat back the Enemy, many of which ran diſorderly away along the neighboring fields. <hi>Doralbo</hi> and <hi>Agenor</hi> had this mean while made interchangeably very great ſlaughter, and bravely imitated by their followers they continued fighting, the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie not appearing to lean to either ſide; but upon the arrival of <hi>Filarbo</hi> and <hi>Theoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro, Agenors</hi> horſe were forc'd to ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by an orderly and ſlow retreat, which could not juſtly be called running: at laſt, after having long indeavoured it, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals met face to face; and <hi>Agenor</hi> aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by almoſt all his men, had at laſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the number of his aſſailants, had not <hi>Doralbo</hi> defending him with his own hands, cryed out, that it belonged to him alone to grapple with that fierce man. Thou ſhalt not ſo eaſily overcome me ſaid <hi>Agenor</hi> with the ſword as with courteſie; having ſaid ſo, he made on with his Scimiter in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121609:48"/>both hands towards <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly evaded that blow which would have cleft a mountain of Iron: at the ſame time he let fly a ſtockado at the Enemies throat, and wounded him ſorely, though not mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, ſo as loſing aboundance of blood, he had almoſt faln down half dead amongſt his own men, but he did not this before he had given <hi>Doralbo</hi> a large but not a deep wound in the ſame left arm whereon he was hurt before. This was the end of this days action, <hi>Agenor</hi> being carried to his Tents, and the Prince upon a very fleet horſe to his Quarters.</p>
            <p>The Armies being muſtered, about 2000 horſe and 3600 foot were found wanting on the Crowns ſide; and on the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths ſide little leſs then 4000 horſe, and only 2700 foot: So as thoſe who defended the Kingdom, had but ſmall cauſe to boaſt of a Victorie purchaſed with ſo much bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doralbo's</hi> wound being tented and dreſt was found to be but ſlight, and no ways dangerous: ſo as he who long'd very much to be where his heart alreadie was, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given order and expreſs command in what was requiſit for the burial of the dead, for the cure of thoſe that were wounded,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121609:49"/>and for all other occurrences which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to the Intereſt of War, which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately recommended to <hi>Filarbo</hi> and <hi>Theocaſtro</hi>'s care, he ſpeedily took his way toward <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> awaited on only by two Gentlemen, and one page. 'Tis hard to imagin, much harder to ſay how many troubled thoughts he was agitated with in this his Journey: he found his heart beat within him for joy to think he ſhould ſo ſoon be made happie in the ſo often wiſht for ſight of his <hi>Niſſena,</hi> from vvhom he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped hereafter for correſpondencie in love, if not more ardent, at leaſt more free and lavvfull; ſhe not being novv bound unto any other affections, ſave to the gratefull matrimonial memorie of her dead husband; he hoped and fear'd: hope and fear being inſeparable from a ſoul in love. He hoped to make himſelf vvorthy of his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veds favour by doing ſome great acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aiming at her ſervice and relief. But he feared leſt ſhe being raiſed to the Regall Throne, might deſpiſe him, who though born a Prince, had no conſiderable fortune, ſave what he might be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of by her, from whom he could not be induced to hope for, or to pretend unto any thing more then ſome little gratitude, in not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121609:49"/>being contemn'd or abhor'd. He thought he had already put a period to <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his pride, that he had trode him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot, cut his throat, and offered him as a victime in ſacrifice to his adored Idoll. Spurre on thy Horſe in Gods name, poor <hi>Doralbo,</hi> thou ſhalt ſhortly ſee to what fatall Spectacles, and ſad misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes thy miſerable deſtiny hath reſerved thee. And thou unhappy one, not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing thy adverſe deſtiny, haſteſt to ſee and hear things and objects which will make thee ſuffer a thouſand deaths. He was ſcarcely come within ſight of the Citie, when he might perceive how much <hi>Nicoſia</hi> was altered for what concern'd him, from what it was when he left it. He was queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned whilſt yet a good way off, by two Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels who were armed, and walked carefully upon a Bulwark, who he was: and not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing him leaſure to reply, they in an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious manner added; That he muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preſently ſtay, or elſe give in his name, and lay down his Arms at the entrance into the Gate: to the which whilſt he drew neer, he was withſtood by a number of Soldiers who kept the Guard. And what, ſaid he in angry manner, is my countenance ſo much alter'd? How now you Raſcals; doe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121609:50"/>you not know me? Then clapping ſpurres to his Horſe, he would force his entry. One of them more raſh then the reſt, laying hold upon his Horſes bridle, ſaid, <hi>Stay Sir, for we are</hi> Mintaurus <hi>his Souldiers, and have no reſpect for you.</hi> At which he reply'd aloud, <hi>Did I not diſdain to defile my ſword in ſo baſe bloud, I would teach thee to diſcourſe thus with a Prince. What is</hi> Mintaurus? <hi>And ſince when commands he over ſuch as I am in</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſia? He would have ſaid more, but the Captain of the Troop coming in, interpoſed himſelfe in ſuch like words: <hi>Sir, theſe may be excuſed, enter in Gods Name, I in the mean while will acquaint him whom I ought to doe ſo, with your Highneſs arrivall.</hi> He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred all ſwoln with anger; nor had he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced far, when he might diſcern ſuch a huſhneſs and melancholy in all the people, as recalling into his mind <hi>Thoas</hi> his death, preſented nothing but confuſion to him, and what miſchiefe might overhang him and <hi>Niſsena;</hi> inſomuch as he found his heart ſtruck through by an unexpected deep melancholy. Troubled with theſe thoughts, he came to the Court Gates, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were likewiſe guarded by a body of men unknown to him. He advanced, being not ſo much reſpected as before: but he did not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121609:50"/>much mind it, his heart leaping within him to think he was ſo near ſeeing and diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his dearly beloved. Being got up the ſtairs, he went towards the Queens Lodgings, and entring into the ante-rooms, he found them void and abandoned by the wonted Guard, and the accuſtomed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quencie of Courtiers, Cavaliers and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men: being entred a little further in, he might hear a whiſpering noiſe as of ſome that were talking. Laying his hand upon the dore <hi>(Oh! go no further</hi> Doralbo, <hi>for thou goeſt not knowing it, to meet with worſe then death)</hi> and opeing it, he found none but two much afflicted Women, who ſtood talking with a page of a misfortune which was befaln. <hi>Where is the Quen,</hi> ſaid he? <hi>has ſhe changed her lodgings?</hi> One of them burſting forth into downright weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, anſwered; <hi>Alas Sir, our Queen may well be ſaid to have changed her lodgings, ſince ſhe is gon to heaven to enjoy the reward of her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, being now free from the power of the wicked Tyrant.</hi> At this ſad and unexpected newes the inamored Prince felt a chilneſs run over his whole body, as is uſual in a cold fit of an ague, and a certain vapor riſe from his heart unto his head, which took his ſight from him, and made him for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121609:51"/>ſtupid, immovable, and ſenceleſs: He afterward brake forth into a loud crie, and ſaid; <hi>Is it true that</hi> Niſſena <hi>is dead? hath the barbarous raſcal murderd her? or who is that barbarous raſcall? where is he? tell me where, and how, and when, and who it was that kill'd her?</hi> The ſorrowfull wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, mingling ſobs and tears with her words, anſwered; <hi>Two Soldiers comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo to do by wicked</hi> Mintaurus, <hi>ript her ſoul from out her boſome with their daggers; the next chamber and her own bed was the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical ſcene of ſo unjuſt an act. Oh my heart! how deadly was the wound; ſavedg beaſts and vipers, not men: but I, I will take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge,</hi> ſaid the Prince, <hi>if I can ſo long out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live my lifes death as to have time to do it; O that I could aſſoon by my death recall her to life.</hi> Lamenting thus, he turn'd his face to the dore of the next chamber, and ſaw the bed and carpets which were ſpread about it upon the ground, and the room it ſelf all ſtained, beſmeared and ſprinkled with bloud. <hi>Oh</hi> ſaid he, <hi>this is my hearts bloud unworthily drawn from that ſpotleſs and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent body. Did I come hither, O</hi> Niſſena, <hi>to ſerve thee, to place thee in thy Throne, to reverence thee, and do I finde nothing of thee but bloudie ſignes? yes, yes, 'twas thus thou
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121609:51"/>meanedſt to point me out the way, that to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and follow thee I muſt die. Be ſure my ſoul I will follow thee, but I will firſt revenge thee: I will firſt have theſe ſtains waſht a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with that Traitor</hi> Mintaurus <hi>his heart-bloud: But good gods! what have theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal monſters done with my Queens body? perhaps her wounds were not mortal. Why then wretch that I am, came not I time enough at leaſt to waſh them with my tears, to binde them up with my lips, and then die? 'twill be time enough though to die when I ſhall have ript his heart from out his boſome, who hath ſlain thee my fair and adored ſoul.</hi> Thus born away by blind fury, he went in haſte from thoſe lodgings, and being reſolved ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to revenge the death of his beloved, or elſe to periſh in the enterpriſe: he went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther where he thought to have found <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurus;</hi> but meeting with <hi>Melaſpus</hi> at the ſtair head, followed by a great many of the Nobility and Souldiers, he preſently laid his hand upon his ſword, crying out, <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the wicked Son of a greater Traytor, and more wicked Father, thou ſhalt the mean while pay for what ſhall afterwards be divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſo infamous a Son and cruell a Father.</hi> His voyce was thunder, his ſword fire, and his arm lightning, wherewith he let flye at
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121609:52"/>
               <hi>Melaſpus</hi> his breaſt; and the wound he gave him being the glory of one onely blow, neither could <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> nor as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as were about him with their Swords all drawn, ſave him from it; ſave onely that falling a little ſide-long, the wound lighted amongſt his ribs, which was intended at his heart; ſtepping a little backward, raſh and deſperate <hi>Doralbo</hi> would have redoubled his thruſt; but <hi>Melaſpus</hi> having already drawn his ſword, and all his followers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing themſelves, or elſe oppoſing the Prince, he could neither hurt any more, nor yet come neer his abhorred enemy. A noiſe and tumult of weapons and voyces was ſuddenly heard throughout the whole Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. Whereupon <hi>Mintaurus</hi> himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, charged that the Rebel and Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor who had trayterouſly indeavoured to kill his ſonne even within the Court, ſhould be taken and bound, but neither ſtruck nor wounded. The valiant Prince laid about him like <hi>Mars,</hi> in defence of his liberty, and wounded four or five of them; but at laſt overcome by the numerous preſs of rude Souldiers, and his weapons taken from him, he was led, or rather carried to a moiſt, narrow, dark Dungeon. <hi>Mintaurus</hi> not knowing that it was deſperation which
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121609:52"/>had made <hi>Doralbo</hi> attempt to kill his ſonne, could not imagine why alone, and armed onely with his Sword, he had expoſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the ſo evident danger of bootleſly loſing his life. He thought this was the beginning of ſome mine laid for his ruine; and fearing leſt he might be inſnared, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a watchfull <hi>Argus</hi> to guard that Kingdome, the Crown whereof he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his own head. That he might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come formidable to ſuch of the Nobility as did not adhere unto him, he the next day made the heads of the Baron <hi>Timis,</hi> and of the Count <hi>Pentaia</hi> be ſtruck off in the midſt of the market-place, pretending that they had backt <hi>Doralbo</hi> in his attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Melaſpus.</hi> He gave great ſummes of money to all the Militia, and changed their Commanders. And that he might win the peoples love, by whom he ſaw himſelfe to be but ſmally eſteemed, and almoſt hated, he gave order for plenty of victuals, and at his own charges bated half their prices. He ſent for ſome from their Governments, changing the Preſidents and chiefe Officers of the Cities and other places: being reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and punctually obeyed by all, out of the cuſtomary uſe he had even in <hi>Thoas</hi> life, freely and with authority to doe ſo, as Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121609:53"/>General. His pleaſure was that <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſpus</hi> ſhould with due circumſpection live in the Kings Palace, and he himſelf retired into the Caſtle, as into a place of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſafety, the poſſeſſion whereof was of great importance to the preſervation of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: Two things onely remain'd to ſettle him in the Kingdom as he thought; the one to disband the Army which was already ſent by the late King againſt the Commonwealth of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> or to make himſelf independent Governor there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: The other to ſecure himſelf for ever of <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who was eſteemed by the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of great power in the Army, and much beloved by the people. The firſt required well weighed determinations and prepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated execution: The ſecond was to be eſtabliſted in the death of the unfortunate Prince. So ſending for the chief Marſhal, he with a frowning countenance ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him, that taking the Headſman a long with him, &amp; as few bloud-ſuckers as he judged neceſſary for the execution, not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any the leaſt mention therof, no not ſo much as in a word, he ſhould go that very night about midnight to the Dungeon where <hi>Doralbo</hi> was, and that having ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled him, he ſhould cauſe his head to be cut
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121609:53"/>off, and bring it ſecretly into the Caſtle to him. O how oft doth the impiety of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men, whilſt it thinkes to triumph over the fall of the innocent, reſt oppreſt by thoſe very ruines which they unjuſtly threatned others withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Niſſena</hi> having acquainted <hi>Eurania</hi> with all the traps and treacheries which ſhe had underſtood was laid and prepared for them by <hi>Mintaurus,</hi> ſhe being a Woman of a great courage, and reſolute wit, betook her ſelf quickly to remedy thoſe evils which threatned not onely the loſſe of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but even the loſſe of their lives. Next morning about break of day, whilſt two women who lay in the Queens lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings were yet aſleep, ſhe clothed her ſelf and made <hi>Niſſena</hi> alſo cloath her ſelf in Pages apparell; and afterwards having horridly beſmear'd the Queens ſheets, &amp; the chamber floor with bloud, which ſhee had formerly prepared ready, ſhe began to cry out, <hi>Ah Traytors! Are Queens thus butchered and murthered in their own Houſes and own Beds? Help, help, Souldiers, Ladies, unleſs you be all confederates in the treaſon. O Traytors! Help, O you good Gods!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this noyſe the Guards haſted into the Chamber, and the women leaping out of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121609:54"/>bed, throwing their clothes about them, and almoſt naked, did the like; whilſt at this very inſtant <hi>Niſſena</hi> and <hi>Eurania</hi> hid themſelves behind the Arras in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward room; and in this confuſed tumult, eſcaped away unknown and unſeen, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of that Chamber, but out of the Court; and being got out of the Citie, went towards the Haven. The Souldiers and women half clad, finding nothing but great quantity of bloud, panting and full of tears, ſought every corner of the lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and ſtruck with amazement, they could not imagine from whence thoſe dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cries could proceed, nor whither the murtherers were fled, and the murthered va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht. They ſpent much time in ſearching, in contemplating the bloudy ſheets and Pavement, and not knowing what to think, nor what to reſolve on: ſome of them ran to acquaint <hi>Mintaurus</hi> with it; who, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened out of a ſound ſleep, was confus'd for a long while, and knew not what to think. Having diſcuſt the matter maturely with himſelf, he gave out Orders, and ſent Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers into all parts to make diligent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry what kind of people had gone out of <hi>Nicoſia</hi> early that morning, and could hear of none but of two young youths who were
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121609:54"/>imagined to be two of the Court Pages, who upon the break of day were gone on foot towards the Sea ſide. Having heard this, he made the guards of the Haven be examined whether any Veſſell had weighed anchor that morning or no, and which way they were bent. He was informed for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that two young youths had at an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant price, hired a Pinace, upon agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that without any intermiſſion of time they ſhould be ſpeedily wafted over to <hi>Rhodes. Mintaurus</hi> gueſt at what was true, and would not ſuffer them to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, being glad that <hi>Niſſena</hi> by her going from <hi>Cyprus,</hi> had ta'ne from him that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impediment which could keep him from freely enjoying the Crown, unleſs he ſhould have uſed ſome violent courſes. The crafty wicked man did notwithſtanding diſſemble the buſineſſe, and ſeeming to beleeve that the Queen was dead, did not onely profeſs and exagerate his innocency, but bewail'd her death, and ſhewed himſelfe ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge it with ſeverity, if he could at any time know who the offender was, or who were his complices, which he with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence ſought after in all places. And the better to colour over theſe his Fictions, the Soldiers who were that night of the Queens
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121609:55"/>Guard, and the two Waiting-women who lay in her rooms, were by his command impriſoned, and ſtrictly examined. He ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well knew how much it made for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of his deſires, that the people ſhould beleeve <hi>Niſſena</hi> to be dead, ſince that he being known to be free from the fact; as indeed he was, he might with eaſe purchaſe the peoples good will, who are apt to alter their inclinations, and that ſo much the more in a caſe wherein they muſt either ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to him, or appear to be partiall to her who was ſuppoſed dead. One thought perplext him, that ſhe being arrived in <hi>Rhodes,</hi> might peradventure obtain ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient aid from Prince <hi>Fermondo</hi> to wage war with him, and endeavour to recover the Kingdome: And though he did not fear his Forces, as farre inferior to thoſe of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> he did partly feare the wrath of Heaven, which his inward ſting of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience did continually threaten him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Niſſena</hi> and <hi>Eurania</hi> met with no ſiniſter adventure, neither in their going from <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> nor when they were gone thence, ſave onely that their journey to the Sea ſide being ſomwhat long, they were ſo weary, as they were neceſſitated to get a Countrey
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121609:55"/>Fellow to be their Guide, who furniſht them with an ill guided horſe, upon the w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they rid by courſe, now one then the other, till they came to the deſired Haven, paying bountifully for their Horſe hire; they hired a <hi>Rhodian</hi> pinace, conditioning that they ſhould preſently put their Oars into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and hoiſt up their Sails, the vvind being Weſtwardly, and good for their intended Navigation. They were forthwith obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, giving themſelves out to be the Queens Pages, vvho for ſome very important buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs were to go for <hi>Rhodes.</hi> The Sun began already to incline toward the Weſt, and they ſaw not as yet any veſſell or ſhip which vvas parted from the <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſhore to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue them, vvhen thinking themſelves either not minded by the Tyrant, or their flight not by him diſcovered, beleeved they vvere free from any purſuit of his. <hi>Eurania</hi> then calling the Pilot of the Pinace to her, made herſelfe freely known unto him, telling him that <hi>Niſsena</hi> vvas the Marquiſs of <hi>Faler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no's</hi> daughter, and now by hereditary ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion Queen of <hi>Cyprus:</hi> He proſtrated himſelfe before their feet, reſting aſſured by their aſpects, and by their manner of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that they had told the truth, and excuſing himſelf for that he had not before
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121609:56"/>uſed himſelfe vvith ſuch obſequiouſneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them as he ought, he ſaid; He thought it fit (if it might ſtand vvith their liking) that they ſhould acquaint him why they went to <hi>Rhodes</hi> under thoſe feigned ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, that he might be the better able to ſerve them with all fitting reſpect. Our voyage (ſaid <hi>Eurania</hi>) muſt not be for <hi>Rhodes,</hi> you muſt tack about towards the North, and carry us to the Army, vvhich is incamped neer <hi>Siuri</hi> and <hi>Pigadia;</hi> for when we ſhall be come thither, vve hope that Prince <hi>Doralbo</hi> vvill by force of Arms place <hi>Niſsena</hi> again upon the Regall Throne, vvhich ſhe hath abandoned for fear of being ſlain by cruell <hi>Mintaurus.</hi> He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged himſelf much obliged to For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, which had bleſt him with ſo happy an occaſion of ſerving them, and aſſured them that unleſs the winds ſhould betray him, he would bring them before midday to land in a little Haven very neer the Army, all the parts of the Iſland being very well known to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doralbo's</hi> unexpected and haſty leaving of the Army, made <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> and <hi>Filarbo</hi> begin to imagine what the urgent occaſion might be which had made him leave them without any reſpect had ſo much as to his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121609:56"/>own health, though grievouſly wounded; and not ſo much as waiting for the next day: They thought it fit to follow him, perſwaded that he had done it out of ſome intereſt wherein the Crown was concern'd; ſo as knowing by report that <hi>Niſsena</hi> was to ſucceed in the Kingdome, and deſirous to ſerve their Couſen in what they were able, they reſolved, that one of them ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take care of the Army, the other ſhould follow the Prince. <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> then departed within a few hours after <hi>Doralbo</hi> was gone, and his brother <hi>Filarbo</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to provide for all things diligently which ſhould be requiſite for the Army till his return. The next night following ſave one, he might ſee two whom at firſt ſight he took to be young youths, enter the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villion; but ſoon finding one of them to be <hi>Eurania,</hi> the other <hi>Niſsena,</hi> cloathed in mans aparrell, he ſaid unto them, What is the good or bad Fortune, Ladies, that hath brought you hither in theſe habits? They drawing him aſide, and making all but his Servants and Friends leave them, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted him with all the troubles which had happened ſince the Kings death: and that finally they might eſcape the danger of loſing their lives, were inforced to fly from
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121609:57"/>
               <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his treacheries, and to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be adviſed by, and to receive timely help from <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who being a man of great authority, and having chief com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Army, was he alone who was able to re-eſtabliſh <hi>Niſſena,</hi> as lawful Queen in the government of the Kingdom, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well that they might ſecurely build upon him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Filarbo</hi> was ſorry that they came ſo late, whilſt the Prince followed by <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> was in unlooked for haſte gone towards <hi>Nicoſia;</hi> but he ſaid they were not notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to deſpair of their pretended ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, he being ready with all the Army o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver which he commanded with a derivato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry power, to be by them imployed as they ſhould be pleaſed. 'Twas reſolved that in the interim they ſhould be kept conceal'd from the knowledge of the Army, till they had reſolved what to do: putting on their womanly apparel, <hi>Doralbo's</hi> Tent was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatly appointed for them, wherein they were to ſtay attended but by ſome few till they ſhould have put on ſome reſolution. When <hi>Niſſena</hi> conſulting only with her own thoughts, began to conſider how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunately ſhe had in vain come from <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſia</hi> to the Camp to finde out her beloved
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121609:57"/>
               <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who amongſt her ſo many miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes was her greateſt care. She ſuffered her ſelf to be ſo carried away with a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent love paſſion, as ſhe could neither eat nor ſleep, but fed her breaſt and eyes only with ſighs and tears. The Prince his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence whoſe merit was already ingraven in her heart, was not the only thing which made her lament; ſhe found her ſelf ſtruck through with thoſe accidents, which by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing her of the fervency of his love, ſhould have rather comforted then afflicted her.</p>
            <p>O how readily (ſaid ſhe within her ſelf) hath my <hi>Doralbo</hi> obeyed my very beck, that ſcarcely come from the battel, and wounded too, he hath with winged feet flown to receive my commands. Unhappy me! Let it not pleaſe the Gods that he be come to <hi>Nicoſia</hi> at a time when he may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve my feigned death to be true: but ſay it be ſo: if it ſhall have ſo faln out, I ſhall at leaſt know with what reſentments of ſorrow and compaſſion he ſhall have wedded my funerals. I ſhall from hence prove his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; alas, I know well enough without any teſtimony, that he loves me as much as a man may love, and I am bound to corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond in love, with him, and ſo I do; ſince
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121609:58"/>whether my fortune be to live a privat wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or to be re-inveſted in the Throne of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> my heart ſhall never be capable of any amorous affection ſave for <hi>Doralbo.</hi> Do thou prove true to me as <hi>I</hi> ſhall do to thee. How much more would ſhe have lamented, if ſhe had known he was in priſon, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death, and perhaps his head ſtruck off. Theſe were her mental diſcourſes when ſhe was alone, but when ſhe diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed either with <hi>Eurania</hi> or <hi>Filarbo,</hi> ſhe tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of nothing elſe but how ſhe might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs her ſelf of the Crown, and if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe indeavoured to hear tidings of <hi>Doralbo,</hi> it was under pretence that his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence would have helped much to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing of her deſignes. <hi>Eurania,</hi> as crafty as a Lady of honeſt and untoucht reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could be, very well underſtood her Nie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces inward paſſions, and having pitty of her, durſt not take any the leaſt notice thereof, fearful leſt ſhe ſhould be offended that others ſhould diſcern and penitrate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe affections, which ſhe deſired to keep conceald as much as poſſibly ſhe could.</p>
            <p>Many days being ſpent in vain in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s and <hi>Theocaſtro</hi>'s re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, or of ſome news from them, and no
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121609:58"/>news being heard, after many conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had and argued too and fro, by <hi>Niſſena, Eugenia,</hi> and <hi>Filarbo,</hi> they all of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſend Ambaſſadors to the Senat of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> to deſire that they would be pleaſed to give audience to a certain perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage who with tvvo only Companions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded leave to be admitted into their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to treat of peace: and in the mean time they would expect <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s return which could not be long: This was done; and thoſe grave Senators did both rejoyce and wonder to hear peace propounded by a victorious Enemy, from whom they had learn'd at the expence of bloud, to fear force, and this they did the rather for that they could expect but little help from <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> wherein was raiſed a terrible fire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. Some of them cautiouſly doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſome Warlick ſtratagem might lie hid under a ſpecious pretence of peace, ſo as they were long in conſulting how the propounded perſonages might be brought into the Senat; at laſt their anſwer was; that they would willingly give them a hearing; on condition notwithſtanding that they ſhould enter the City unarmed, and with their eyes blindfoulded. according to cuſtom.</p>
            <pb n="114" facs="tcp:121609:59"/>
            <p>All this while there was no news of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo</hi>'s return, whereat <hi>Niſſena</hi> was ſo much afflicted, as he muſt have had a Tygers heart who would not have pittied her if ſhe had as openly demonſtrated her paſſions, as ſhe kept them conceal'd. The day was come, nay the very hour wherein the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from the Camp were to be brought to the Senat of <hi>Famagoſta,</hi> and preſently it was noiſed throughout the whole Army, that <hi>Niſſena</hi> by right of ſucceſſion Queen of <hi>Cyprus</hi> was ſhe who accompanied by <hi>Eura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> and <hi>Filarbo,</hi> would by her going into the Enemies Citie put an end to the War, and conclude a well ſettled peace. She paſt through the midſt of the Army all covered over vvith a ſad black mantle, but her fair countenance, her vvhite boſome, and her lively eyes ſhevved a Majeſtie ſo ſvveetly ſevere as ſhe made her ſelf at once be both feared and adored: She paſt through the Army reverenced and adored as a Goddeſs: For vvhereſoever <hi>Mars</hi> governs, <hi>Venus</hi> finds alvvaies obſequious and devout hearts. The Commiſſioners vvere vvaited for by tvvo chief Officers of the Senat at that gate of the Town which led towards the Camp: where <hi>Niſſena</hi> being come, alighted out of the Coach, and led underneath the arms by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121609:59"/>
               <hi>Eurania</hi> and <hi>Filarbo,</hi> the Officers of <hi>Fama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſta</hi> ſtood amazed no leſs at her beauty then at the unuſual novelty of the Ambaſſy, when they bound her eyes they in a low voice within themſelves complained that they were to rob the people of the pleaſing object of thoſe eyes, which were unworthy to be covered, had it not been pretended that like ſacred things, they were to be hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den underneath a vail. Thus ſaid theſe two gray heads, at once both admiring and making themſelves merry with <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s more then human beautie: But they ſtood muſing not without ſuſpition of ſome fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture evil to what end this unuſual Treaty of Women might be. Being admired by the people, ſhe came into the Senat, nor need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this faireſt Oratrice to win their attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by any artificial Rhetorick, ſince all the Senators with their eyes fixt upon her, ſtood expecting what graceful and eloquent ſpeech was to proceed from that mouth, which was ſo rich in treaſures. Some of them, whoſe hearts were not frozen, though ſnow lay on their hair, ſaid with fitting vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity; How is it poſſible that ſhe ſhould treat of peace, whilſt at the very firſt aſpect her countenance intimates War? Having made her requiſit reverence, and being ſat
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:121609:60"/>on a chair which was prepared for her, whilſt <hi>Eurania</hi> and <hi>Filarbo</hi> ſtood retir'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, ſhe ſpake thus.</p>
            <p>That fire of War, which with barbarous flames hath hitherto unduly imbroyl'd and conſumed the felicity of peace even to aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which hath waſted the fruit of the fields, exhauſted the treaſure of Exchequers, and been the death of thoſe Subjects who have as gloriouſly as unopportunely ſhed their bloud and loſt their lives, is quencht: The fire of War, I ſay, moſt grave and wiſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nators, is quencht: nor do I come hither to invite you to lay down arms, or to treat of peace, but to pronounce peace already e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed and concluded between your Commonwealth, and our Kingdom of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> Wonder not that I ſpeak of peace already concluded and eſtabliſhed: I very well know that in a Senat whoſe wiſdom hath always been equal to their unwreſted and immaculate Juſtice, Juſtice muſt alſo equal their impeccable and always conſtant wiſdom. I ſpeak of that Juſtice, by which upon ſo many occurrences, and affairs as well of Peace as War, you have delated the fame of your glory, not only through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole circuit of this Iſland, but alſo throughout the whole World, which
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121609:60"/>ſeems now too narrow a circuit to contain the noiſe thereof. I ſpeak of that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the leaſt glories whereof are, the preſerving of your Liberties unviolated, though ſubject to a regal Scepter, and in this Liberty, the ſo bounding the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ambition and authority, as all of you being equall Lords and Commanders, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſtrives who ſhall moſt willingly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to anothers Government, knowing at once both how to obey and command. By this Juſtice, and this Wiſdom, I ſee peace already granted to my propoſals, though theſe vertues never appeared more eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt you, then in your ſo generouſly taken up Arms of late againſt this Crown. I ſay the occaſions of raiſing this Warre have been in you no leſs juſt, then was your Wiſdom. How could you moſt grave Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, more wiſely or more juſtly ſhew your reſentment of a Kings proceedings, who requiring a Contribution from you impoſſible for you to disburſe, vvould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force you to be diſobedient, that he might pretend to a lavvfull occaſion of taking from you your Senatorie Authoritie, and by deſtroying a Commonvvealth, vvhich hath for ſo many ages injoy'd an Ariſtocraticall Government? Alas! your Juſtice and your
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:121609:61"/>Wiſdom could not be more worthily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; but neither could your Juſtice nor your Wiſdome be more unjuſtly betraid by an infamous and wicked Miniſter of State, who falſifying the Kings Seals, and abuſing the authority wherwith he was undeſerving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intruſted, made falſe reports be ſpread abroad amongſt you, not onely by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Orders in publick Senat, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt privat men by lying letters, that the intentions of that beſt and gracious King aimed at framing pretences to raiſe a warre, whereby he might pretend to bereave you not onely of the Name, Priviledges, and authority, but even of the eſſence of a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>This was the Traytor <hi>Mintaurus,</hi> who raiſed up to wealth by Fortune, to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his naturall Lord and Maſter, and to dignities, ſeeing the King left without ſucceſſion, grew ſo greedily in love with the Scepter, as to arrive at the managing thereof, he hath endeavoured and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the moſt execrable villanies which could be wrought, I will not ſay by Man, but by any Infernall Fury. He was the wicked poyſoner, who not to ſee his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived hopes of reigning thrown to the ground by <hi>Thoas</hi> his marriage, did by
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121609:61"/>mortiferous poyſon cauſe Death be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with his meat; whence in ſtead of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the joyes of a Nuptiall Bed, he is fatally and unfortunately paſt to the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the grave. This was the ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous couſener, who to diſturb the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of that marriage which might hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his arrivall at the Goal of his complot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ends, made her who was deſtin'd to be the Kings wife, beleeve by falſe advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he would make her partner of his bed, not as his lawfull wife, but as his diſhoneſt whore. He is that cruell Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, who after having wickedly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefully bereft him of life from whom he ought to acknowledge whatſoever he hath of greatneſs, glory, or riches; hath not onely hinder'd that <hi>Niſſena</hi> from peacefully ſucceeding to the Inheritance, who was by <hi>Thoas</hi> at his laſt expiring breath, with all cordiality left heir to the Kingdome, but hath uſurped her authority, laid ſnares for her life, ta'ne from her her liberty; and finally, ſtoln the Crown from her. He is the unworthy Tyrant who now unjuſtly ſits upon the Regall Throne of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> having raiſed himſelfe thereunto by cruelty, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, murder, injuſtice, and by the down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall of others. Let that ſame juſtice and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:121609:62"/>wiſdome then, grave Senators, which moved you to take up Arms againſt a King who was always partial to your intereſts, excite you to peace with your lawfull Queen, and to revenge againſt that infamous ſubverter of the common quiet. This doth very wel become your juſtice and wiſdome too hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly offended and abuſed. You ow this in charity to her innocency, who by me implores help and ſuccour from you. From you it is that ſhe may have the Fortune to acknowledge her Kingdome, Liberty and Life, if by joyning our Forces together we ſhall goe to throw down that unworthy one from the Throne, who hath known how to make you appear unwiſe and unjuſt, who hath known how to ſteal a Scepter, and who will know how to tyrannize over his ſubjects, and make impiety triumph eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where. From you the people ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their happineſs, the Queen her Scepter, and the Gods themſelves reſpects and victims. Let it not be ſaid that Laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be leveld, or Swords ta'ne in hand ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by your or our Souldiers in offence of one another, but let us joyntly and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly turn our Arms to the ruine of that wicked Tyrant, of that enemy to our quiet, of that betrayer of our Liberty, to the moſt
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:121609:62"/>barbarous, diſloyall, and moſt wicked man of as many as this day live. Let us run to revenge our Souldiers faln in the laſt Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, and let us offer as a Sacrifice to their ſhadows vvho doe require it of us, the damn'd Deceiver, who hath been the fatall occaſion of ſo much bloud and death. Let us go to purchaſe unto our ſelves by a ſhort and eafie warre, a long and quiet peace; nay rather let us goe to a glorious and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain triumph. Let us goe then you who are as wiſe as generous. The untild and unma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nur'd grounds oppreſt, and as it were groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning under the Footſteps of fierce Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, under the Iron Hoofs of warlike Horſes, and under the weight of warlike Engines, doe with flowry eloquence intreat it at our hands. Fruitfull mothers fearing to ſee their children die by the unjuſt Ax, intreat it at our hands. Brides doe intreat us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, fearing leſt they may ſhortly bewaile the loſſe of their beloved Conſorts either ſhut up in priſon or put to death upon the Gallows. We have the prayers of young Virgins for this, not ſure to keep the flower of their virginity unviolated under the government ef ſo perverſe a Ruler, who wil always foment luſt and wickedneſs. Tender Babes from out their Cradles, with tears, &amp;
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:121609:63"/>mouths new puld from their mothers breaſts, intreat us hereunto, being ſure to have their innocency trampled under foot under the ſhadow of a Scepter, which will protect and fauter triumphant faults. And finally, I <hi>Niſſena</hi> of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance lawfull Succeſſor of the Crown of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> the which doth as juſtly belong to me, as it hath been by <hi>Mintaurus</hi> unjuſtly poſſeſt, 'tis I who beg this of you. The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of due belongs to me, who wife to the late <hi>Thoas,</hi> was by him in his life time crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Queen, &amp; in his death confirmed in the Dominion. I, as ſuch a one, doe both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and offer peace; and being betraid and oppreſt, I flie to you for juſtice and aſſiſtance. Let us then unite our forces I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, and let us carry the War home to his gates who hath ſubverted peace. Nor will it be without glory to your renowned valor, that the Tyrant be by your means puniſht, and be by you hurld down to his own bloud from his uſurped Throne. Let us goe, for I invite you to peace, glory, and victory.</p>
            <p>Here ſhe held her peace: Nor was there any one in that great and grave Aſſembly, who did not joyfully and humbly offer to expoſe their own perſons to any the greateſt
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121609:63"/>danger which might tend to remit her into her juſt and lawfull poſſeſſion of the crown. In the mean time they ſtrove who ſhould firſt come with bended knees to ſhew vvith obſequiouſneſs their duty to her Majeſty. They placed her in the worthieſt and moſt eminent place, whilſt they with their hats off ſtood on foot; proteſting unto her by the mouths of the beſt ſpoken men amongſt them, their ancient devotion towards the Crown of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and complaining of that falſe deceiver, who by abuſive fraud had neceſſitated them to take up arms againſt their King, at all other times, and upon all other occaſions reſpected and honored by them as became them. They thanked her for the proffered peace, which they willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted of, proteſting themſelves much bound unto her for that ſhe was pleaſed to make uſe of them to recover her Kingdom. They offered unto her not onely the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick moneys, but even the moneys of their privat purſes, as much of their Army as was left; and finally, they acknowledged her, and bowed unto her as their lawfull Queen, ſwearing eternall and inviolable al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to her, Whilſt theſe Welcomes vvere exerciſed there, the Ladies of the Citie were advertiſed, that the exceeding
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121609:64"/>fair Lady, who not long before was come thither under a pretence of Ambaſſie, was the Queen <hi>Niſſena,</hi> the merit of whoſe beauty had raiſed her to the Crown, and of whom they had formerly heard. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they, to pay their due reſpects to ſo great a Princeſſe, and out of curioſitie to ſee whether her beauty did anſwer to the fame thereof, putting on their richeſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments and beſt aparrell, they went in guilded Coaches to the Palace, to ſerve and reverence her. The newes of the concluded peace vvas this mean while ſpread abroad amongſt the people, with which all the Citizens and common people being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, did every where applaud the Queens beauty and wiſdome. She came forth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by the Ladies and Senators, many whereof waited upon her to the Camp, whilſt the common people, that they might alſo ſee a beauty which knew how to merit Kingdoms, by the noiſe of Trumpets and beating up of Drums, fild the Heavens with ſhouts of <hi>Jubilee</hi> and rejoycing. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'twas night, the chief Commanders of the lately before enemies Army, came to her Pavillion on the Senats behalf, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive her commands: offering themſelves to march with their <hi>Militia,</hi> whitherſoever
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:121609:64"/>ſhe ſhould command them, ſhe received them in a grave and courteous manner, ſending them back preſented vvith ſome little Jevvels vvhich ſhe had carried vvith her vvhen ſhe fled from <hi>Nicoſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This mean while conſultation was had how and in what manner they were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and <hi>Niſſena</hi> thinking ſhe had put the means already in a fair way whereby ſhe might repoſſeſs her ſelf of her Crown, had now nothing to afflict her ſelf with, but the thought of her <hi>Doralbo,</hi> of whom hearing no news, ſhe could little rejoyce at any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good ſucceſs, which either had or could happen unto her, She could not ſo much conceal this diſquiet of her mind, but that ſhe gave expreſs command that before the Armies ſhould march towards <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> two of the moſt experienc'd and crafty Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſhould be ſent to learn ſome news of the Prince and of <hi>Theocaſtro,</hi> and at the ſame time to find with what number of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers the Citie was guarded, and in what condition of peace and ſafetie <hi>Mintaurus</hi> and <hi>Melaſpus</hi> were with the people, whether beloved or hated: whether they behaved themſelves as Lords and Kings, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but as Officers of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>VVhen <hi>Filarbo</hi> and <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> as hath
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121609:65"/>been ſaid before, ſaw <hi>Doralbo</hi> though wounded go from the Camp towards <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſia,</hi> they thought it fit to follow him, whereupon not many hours after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> took the ſame way. He came to the Citie at that fatal inſtant, when the Prince, deſperat out of <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved death, having indeavoured to kill <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſpus,</hi> was committed to Priſon. So as hearing of his being in hold, he thought it good to keep himſelf conceal'd, leaſt he might be thought guilty as complice of the attempted Homicides, and that he might the better obſerve what they reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to do with the Prince, to the end that he might aſſiſt him, and purchaſe if it were poſſible, his ſafetie and libertie, though it ſhould coſt him his life. Getting to this purpoſe into a friends houſe on whoſe fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie he might relie, he deſired to know what urgent occaſion had induced <hi>Doralbo</hi> to ſo ſtrange and unadviſed a reſolution: and he was informed, that being provoked by his exceeding anger at the Queens ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed death, he reſolved to revenge her, whoſe death was afterwards found to be falſe, but that it was true that ſhe was fled to <hi>Rhodes.</hi> He lamented his Couſins misfortune, but much more <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121609:65"/>as being more grievous and more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent; he being impriſoned, and expoſed to the arbitrarie judgment of an unjuſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere independent, and interreſſed Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, from whom in all probabilitie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but cruel reſentments could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. He reſolved therefore that very night to diſcover what <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions were againſt the impriſoned Prince; and to this purpoſe he ſent to the Lord Chancellor in the name of one of the chief Lords of the Court, to know whether ſentence were alreadie pronounced againſt <hi>Doralbo</hi> or no, as being already convinc'd of the Fact, ſo as all proceſs or examination would prove ſuperfluous. He could learn nothing from him, but that <hi>Mintaurus</hi> had ſent for the chief Marſhal, and given him ſome privat directions. <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> growing hereby more deſirous of informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, would go himſelf, protected by the darkneſs of the night, to know of the chief Marſhal, who was his familiar friend, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Doralbo</hi> were in any eminent danger of death or no; This man lived near the Court, and from his Lodgings (where he his wife, and children lived)there was a paſſage through a narrow tarrace to a pair of ſtairs which landed in a common little
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:121609:66"/>yard, but not much frequented, wherein were the firſt gates of the under-ground Priſons, in the worſt and moſt incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious whereof, the unfortunate Prince <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralbo</hi> was ſhut in, whoſe head by the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants command was to be ſtruck off. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtro</hi> tarried till the night was well advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and then himſelf accompanied by his friend and one ſervant, went unknown, and as ſecretly as could be, to the Marſhals ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, when coming near his gate, he might hear him chide his wife and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters aloud, for that having alreadie ſupt, they did not haſte to make his bed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he might for ſome two hours take his reſt, what unuſual haſte is this that you are in, reply'd one of his daughters? and why no more then tvvo hours reſt? to whom he fetching a deep ſigh reply'd: Alas that I might reſt all night in my bed, but I muſt ere long riſe, and go with the heads-man and ſome Soldiers, to take off unfortunate Prince <hi>Doralbo's</hi> head; who by a raſh, but truly a generous action hath this day deſerv'd to die. Divers words paſt after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards betvveen the father, vvife and daughters, vvhich <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> did not very perfectly underſtand, vvho had heard ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make him depart anger'd, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:121609:66"/>beſides himſelf; in ſo much as he ſpoke not a vvord till he vvas come to his friends houſe vvhere he lay. <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> took his friend aſide into a chamber, and then vvith a ſad and melancholy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, vented to him his painfull paſſion vvhich oppreſt him for <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death: and reſolved howſoever, he would venture his life to ſave him; he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto him a means which might eaſily ſucceed, if he and four other armed men would ſecond his reſolutions. He put him in minde of the Prince his deſerts, from whom he might expect to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully requited, if ſo be the enterpriſe ſhould prove ſucceſsfull. He minded him of his obligation, which as <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s Couſin, in whoſe revenge it was that <hi>Doralbo</hi> had done what he did, bound him to whatſoever dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous attempt. How they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by her, if ſhe ſhould regain her Kingdom; and finally he call'd unto his mind the publique good in <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his downfall, whom he was aſſured he could infallibly kill: but that all was ſuddenly to be reſolved upon, and to be put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it being of neceſſity to be done within a few hours. His friend being all heart and courage, wholoved no leſs <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s worth
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:121609:67"/>and valour, then he hated <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his Tyranny, offered himſelf ready to do any thing; and chuſing two of his ableſt and truſty ſervants, they provided themſelves all four of excellent Arms, and leaving their own houſe went towards the chief Marſhals Lodgings. They were not gone a bow-ſhot forward, when two Gentlemen that were brethren, but enemies to <hi>Mintau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his faction, knocking at the gate of a noble Palace, deſired help and aſſiſtance; they rejoyced to ſee themſelves aſſiſted not only by them, but by two of their ſwagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing companions, who were thought to be the beſt and moſt reſolute blades of all <hi>Nicoſia.</hi> They in a ſhort time arrived very huſh and quiet at the little yard by which the way lay to the Marſhals Lodgings: nor had they ſtaid there long when they might hear a noiſe out of a window, as of the clattering of keys, and of men who ſpoke loud enough; Theſe were the Jai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and the dog-leeches who were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to cut off unfortunate <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s head, who coming in to haſten the chief Marſhal, made ready the priſon keys, and it being now ſomewhat late and a fitting time, were ready for the tragical execution. As they came out into the Tarrace, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtro</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:121609:67"/>and his Companions withdrew themſelves aſide, and they having deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſtairs, opened the firſt gate, and entring in, would have ſhut it again, when they might ſee themſelves aſſaulted by the armed and reſolute Companions, and heard themſelves threatned with preſent death, if they did not inſtantly without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, or ſo much as breathing, deliver the keys unto them, and ſerve them quietly as a guide to the Priſon wherein the condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prince was. It was bootleſs for thoſe Officers to defend themſelves, or by their outcries to call in help, which had they done, they would aſſuredly have haſtened their threatned death; and 'twas impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for them to be heard from that lote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean place, let them have cryed never ſo loud: the firſt gate being already ſecured on the inſide by the provident Gentlemen. To fight valliantly with their ſwords in hand, was not to be expected from baſe puſillanimous men, whoſe births and ſouls were as abject as was their profeſſion. Not able to do otherwiſe, they reſolved to obey: 'twas better for them to expoſe themſelves to the hazard of a future and uncertain death, then to what was moſt certain and preſent. <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> knowing them to be
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:121609:68"/>cowardly and baſe ſpirited, ſaid unto them with voice of terror: If you will readily obey our command, I will promiſe you both life and reward; if not, you are all dead men. Open thoſe gates there quickly hoe, and tell me as quickly what unjuſt act you were comanded to do by the Tyrant. Sir! ſaid the chief Marſhall, with a quive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring voice, the heavens know how contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it is to my genius to be imployed in ſuch like affairs, but the Fates will have it ſo. We are ſervants, and muſt ſerve by force, if not by good will. I humbly and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively aſſigne over into your protection my life, and the lives of theſe men which are now aies ſafe from <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, if I do not before midnight be over, preſent him with <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s head. Advance and let us in, replied <hi>Theocaſtro,</hi> thou ſhalt preſent him with the Princes head, but in another manner then he expects. Whilſt they were thus diſcourſing they came to the dore which was alreadie open, and which opened into the narrow moiſt noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and dark dungeon, in which with his hands ſtraight tied together with a cord, the ſad and alreadie languiſhing Prince ſtood leaning againſt the wall; he was not able to indure the torch light, being diſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:121609:68"/>from light, wherefore he turn'd his face from them whilſt he thus ſpake: How now my friends, the hour of my death is now come, is it not? yes, yes, draw near boldly, let the wicked Tyrant glut himſelf with my bloud, for death does no whit diſmaie me, ſave only that I could not firſt revenge the death of that innocent fair one whom none but that barbarous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low could have the heart ſo cruelly to kill. Death is to me moſt welcome, which will open the ſame way unto me through which my ſoul is alreadie paſt; miſerable <hi>Doral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi> how great is thy misfortune, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born a Prince, muſt die by the hands of a hangman: but patience; come near I ſay, give me only ſo much leave as I may pronounce and often repeat <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s name, and then let the fatal blow come; for I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nor beg nothing more at your hands but that I may breath forth my ſoul with that beloved name in my mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> appearing then ſmilingly before him, ſaid, <hi>Talk not of Death, Sir, where your ſervant</hi> Theocaſtro <hi>is; here am I, with theſe my faithfull friends, ready either to free you out of priſon, or nobly to loſe our lives together with you. Now tis that you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call unto you that generoſity and valor which
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121609:69"/>was born with you.</hi> Niſſena <hi>lives, Sir, and we will all live to his ſhame and confuſion who hath occaſioned theſe troubles: Come out from this noyſome hole, and joyfully follow me.</hi> The tears guſht into <hi>Doralbo's</hi> eyes for joy, when he heard that <hi>Niſſena</hi> was alive, who weeping almoſt down-right, ſpoke thus, <hi>It would not much import, my friend, though you ſhould abuſe me in promiſing me my life and liberty; but your ſin would not be ſmall, if you ſhould tell a falſhood that</hi> Niſſena <hi>lives. Is it true that ſhe is alive? She lives, ſhe lives, Sir,</hi> (reply'd Theocaſtro) <hi>'tis not I that doe deceive you, 'tis you your ſelfe, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving her to be dead, would unſeaſonably and precipitouſly revenge that death which ſhe did not ſuffer. She and</hi> Eurania <hi>to eſcape</hi> Mintaurus <hi>his violence, fled away: and to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitate and ſecure their eſcape, they cunningly left the bed and floor all beſmear'd with blood.</hi> At theſe words <hi>Doralbo</hi> cheered up, and his hands being untied by one of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that accompanied <hi>Theocaſtro,</hi> he had the chief Marſhals weapons given him; who, together with the reſt of his Officers, was forced to lay them down, and to take an oath that they would doe whatſoever ſtould be commanded them. They reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to wrap up ſomewhat or other, it mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121609:69"/>not what which ſhould be about the bulk or Bookdome of <hi>Doralbo</hi>'s head, with the which the chief Marſhall going before, might guide them all into the Caſtle where <hi>Mintaurus</hi> was, who had formerly given order unto the Guard, that about that hour they ſhould ſuffer any of the Officers of Juſtice to come in, and ſtood longing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expecting, to ſee in that hated head his ſons revenge, and himſelf in a good part ſecured of the Kingdome. They paſt, not meeting with any interruption, to the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber door, wherein the Tyrant lay in Bed, but awake, reading ſome letters which he had received from divers of the Preſidents, who acquainted him with affairs belonging to the Kingdome. The fatall houre, <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurus,</hi> is arrived, wherein thou muſt paſs from this life, to give an account to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Gods, for thy ſo many and ſo execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſdoings; and thou dreameſt of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs then dying. Thus doth Heaven puniſh the wicked, when they do leaſt think on't. <hi>Doralbo</hi> entred firſt with a Dagger drawn in his right hand, and followed by the reſt: he flew towards the bed with ſo ſudden a force, as the Tyrant ſeeing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo unexpectedly ſet upon by him, whom he conceived to be already behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121609:70"/>he could not for very fear ſpeak ſo much as one word: ſave that when he had received four or five ſtabs, he cryed out, <hi>You have overcome, O you Traytors:</hi> and wallowing in his own bloud, upon the ſame Bed wherein he thought ſhortly to take quiet reſt, he remain'd a dead, bloudy, and horrid Karkaſs, as an example to all raſh men, who think it lawfull to provoke the Divine anger with reiterated faults, perſwading themſelves that they ſhall eſcape unpuniſhed. It remained now for the Prince and his companions to ſecure the Caſtle; but it was firſt reſolved that <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtro</hi> ſhould immediatly get out of the Citie, and make with all ſpeed for <hi>Rhodes,</hi> where the publick report was that <hi>Niſſena</hi> was gone. At whoſe deſires he might very well hope, that Prince <hi>Fermondo</hi> would not refuſe two well arm'd Gallies, fraught with good ſtore of Souldiers; the which the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant being dead, and <hi>Doralbo</hi> commanding the Caſtle, would ſuffice to reinveſt her in her Throne; or if ſhe her ſelf would come along, ſhe ſhould find many of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity who would ſide with her, and be ſure to have the adherence of all the common people; ſo as with thoſe few people which ſhe ſhould bring with her, ſhe might eaſily
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:121609:70"/>recover the Crown. Long conſultation was had whether the ſmall Garriſon which did guard the Caſtle, was to be won by threats, or by gold, great ſtore of which vvas found in <hi>Mintaurus</hi> his cheſts: but the very noyſe that Prince <hi>Doral'o</hi> had made himſelfe maſter thereof, and had kild the Tyrant, was ſufficient to make the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers come of themſelves, and offer their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to him; by whom being received as became a Prince, and rewarded with good ſummes of money, they ſwore to be faithful to him till death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> went forth upon his intended enterpriſe, and the draw bridge being hoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted up, and the Percullis let down, <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taurus</hi> his body was hung out upon a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the Caſtle which was moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the view of the Citie. The ſight of this horrid and unlook'd for ſpectacle the next morning, caus'd joy in many, in others fear, and in all men wonder. I am not able to expreſs into what raging fury <hi>Melaſpus</hi> fell when he heard this fatall acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. All men diſcourſed diverſly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as they vvere particularly addicted or inclin'd, how and by whom ſo great and dangerous a deed could be effected; but underſtanding that the priſon gates ſtood
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121609:71"/>open wherein <hi>Doralbo</hi> was ſhut up, and that the chiefe Marſhall, and ſome other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Officers vvere miſſing, they all of them did partly gueſſe vvhat the matter might be. Fooliſh <hi>Melaſpus</hi> ſuppoſing himſelf betrayed, and not knowing by vvhom, fell into ſuch threatning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate ſpeeches, as did diſpleaſe many even of his own faction: he vvould blow up the Caſtle, bury his Father under the ruines of the vvhole Citie, make Rivers run vvith human bloud, and kill a great many that were innocent; ſo as amongſt ſo many any one might be met vvithall vvho vvas guilty of his Fathers death, or had but the leaſt hand in it. And yet by all theſe threats and violences the unwary young man got nothing but the generall hatred both of the Nobility and common people. Many dayes were not paſt, vvhen yet to his further vexation, nay even to the reducing him to deſpair, he heard news by a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, vvho came running, out of breath, that a numerous Army vvhich came from the Eaſt, over-ſpread all the Countrey, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming towards <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> and that they could not at that time be above twenty miles off. Inraged and biting his fingers ends, he in a diſdainfull manner broke forth into theſe
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121609:71"/>vvords, <hi>I ſee you unjuſt Heavens, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imploy your maligne Influences but to my prejudice, for which if I cannot for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſhew any reſentment, I will not howſoever die unrevenged; I will likewiſe learn to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh gallantly. Let them come, let my enemies haſten to bereave me of my life, for I am ready to dye, but I will firſt make my ſelf a Tomb of their Karkaſſes. Let them come, they ſhall not find me running away, but ready to ſtand their ſhock.</hi> Thus he ſpent two hours, or thereabouts, blaſpheming the Gods, and curſing his perverſe ſtars; but at laſt his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger breathing a little over, he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to more peacefull, and leſſe imprudent thoughts, he reſolved to withdraw himſelf from his preſent misfortune, hoping to get to <hi>Soria,</hi> and by his Wealth, Wit, and Gallantry, to return again to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and to regain his fortune by the bloud and ruine of his enemies. Having heaped up as much gold, and as many jewels as he could, he vvent vvith ſome of his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt and deareſt friends, towards the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where having hired an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man of War, he lancht immediatly into the Deep, where fortune appeared yet more adverſe unto him. His Veſſell was not well got into the <hi>Iſsican</hi> Gulf, when it muſt ſuffer it
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:121609:72"/>ſelf to be diſpoſed of at the pleaſure of an impetuous wind, which blowing from the North, made the ſhip take a clean contrary Road from what it was bound for. They ſunk their Anchors to ſtay the violence of their courſe; but their greateſt Cable being burſt in two by a violent guſt of wind, they were toſſed too and fro for three nights and two dayes by the ſtorm; which after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving hurld them every where about thoſe Seas, left them at laſt becalm'd with their ſhip all torn, a day and a halfes ſail from <hi>Cyprus</hi> to the Eaſtward.</p>
            <p>By how much <hi>Melaſpus</hi> misfortune was in plowing up the Seas, ſo much the more ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfull was <hi>Theocaſtro's</hi> voyage in a light Pinnace towards <hi>Rhodes;</hi> whether being come, he heard that that very day <hi>Niſſena's</hi> funerals were celebrated, the being bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for dead by her friends, and by the whole Iſland. Of which the better to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure himſelf, he went directly to the Temple of <hi>Pallas,</hi> where in dolefull pomp this ſad ſolemnity was to be celebrated. He was aſtoniſhed, and wept at this unexpected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident; but his grief and aſtoniſhment la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted not long: For meeting with a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who was much his friend, and who embracing him, welcom'd his return to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121609:72"/>
               <hi>Rhodes. Theocaſtro</hi> being impatient, asked him how and when <hi>Niſſena</hi> died? You are better able to acquaint us with the manner &amp; time thereof, reply'd his friend; for foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I beleeve you are now come from <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and ought to know all the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the death of the unfortunately betrayd <hi>Niſsena.</hi> How, ſaid <hi>Theocaſtro,</hi> did ſhe not die here at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> whither ſhe fled to ſave her ſelfe from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits &amp; treachery of the Tyrant <hi>Mintaurus?</hi> She is ſo far from being dead in <hi>Rhodes,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the other as ſhe hath notbin ſeen here; but we received certain &amp; publick advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that by direction from the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Tyrant, ſhe was barbarouſly wounded and ſlain, as ſhe lay in bed. So, ſo, the Gods be praiſed, ſaid <hi>Theocaſtro, Niſſena</hi> is not dead, though her funerals be celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted here. I came three dayes ſince from <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſia,</hi> where the common report is that ſhe is here, and I am come hither to bring her good news, and it may be to carry her back with me to take poſſeſſion of the Kingdom. But for Gods ſake, before the truth of this be publickly known, let us ſee the ſad ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity celebrated, at the vvhich vve may aſſiſt the leſs ſorrowfully, in that we know 'tis done for one that is alive: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121609:73"/>rather to be laughed at then lamented.</p>
            <p>They went to the Temple, which being built by skilfull artificers in a no very large ſquare figure, gloried in white Marble, though then all covered over with black Velvet, all imbroidered over and richly wrought with gold and ſilver, and at fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting diſtances Imperial Crowns daſht to pieces; broken Scepters, and huge Pearl ſhaped <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto tears, to the end that at ſo fatal a ſpectacle the very walls might ſeem to weep. From the higheſt Tribunal, ſhaped in a perfect round, and all vailed over with black, divers Cupidons hung upon undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcernable threads of braſs, weeping, and in ſeveral poſtures with torches lighted in their hands, ſeemed as if they flew in the air. Underneath another leſſer Tribunal juſt oppoſit to the chief Porch, an altar was raiſed trampled on by a ſtatue of Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, which cloathed in mourning mantles, having on her breaſt a black breaſtplate, and on her head a helmet of like hue, held a launce in her right hand, and in her left a buckler or ſhield, wherein was cut agaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Gorgons head, and which as the Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral laſted, vomited forth artificial fires from its gaping mouth, and ill looking eies: in the midſt of the Temple there ſtood a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:121609:73"/>ſquare half pace, of a well proportioned height, adorned with handſome corniſhes, and other artificial peeces of Architecture, the materials whereof ſeemed to be of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt touchſtone, and from the eyes and mouths of certain antick faces which lay thereon, great ſtore of perfumed flames guſht out. Over the half pace ſtood a Ballaſter, on whoſe uppermoſt Corniſh ſweet ſmelling inſence fumed forth from odd faſhioned races, hung at equal diſtance; from thence the three Graces made of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Alabaſter, ſerved for pedeſtals to a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacious Fountain, the more miraculous and lovely for that inſtead of water, it in divers places ran in rivolets of fire. In midſt of this pile ſtood a naked <hi>Cupid</hi> weeping, and having his eyes bound up, and which was upheld with an Atlas curiouſly cut out in red Marble, from whoſe quiver burſt out continual torrents of flames to ſupply the Urne which ſtood beneath with combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble materials. Thus with great demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of publick ſorrow, did Prince <hi>Fermondo</hi> and all the people of <hi>Rhodes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail the death of that <hi>Niſſena,</hi> whoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty if it had given her a Kingdom, it had (as was given out in that Iſland) by an unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy change, bereft her of life.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:121609:74"/>
            <p>I mention not the quality of the Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other ceremonies which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſed in thoſe Temples upon ſuch like occaſions, becauſe our ages have not been acquainted therewithall. The two Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen did both admire and laugh at this noble Funeral Pomp, which by how much more ſtately it was, was ſo much the more vain, and worthy to be laughed at, becauſe her ſad cold aſhes were therein celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, who was never better pleaſed, nor more content then at that hour. The Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals being ended <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> went to ſee his friends and kindred, whom he acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the falſhood of <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s reported death, and told them that inſtead of bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her as dead, he hoped they would ſhortly ſolemnize her aſſumption to the Kingdom; wherein ſhe would be the more glorious and happie by her arriving there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at through the midſt of a thouſand treaſons and treacheries in vain plotted againſt her by <hi>Mintaurus.</hi> He told them all that had hapned, and then going to kiſs Prince <hi>Fermondo</hi>'s hands, he moved both wonder and mirth in him, by witneſſing that <hi>Niſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> was alive, for the recovery of whoſe Kingdom he deſired him to aſſiſt her only with two well arm'd Gallies; for which he
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:121609:74"/>might afterward at all times and upon all occaſions, expect the like requital from the Queen, who would in a great part acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the recovery of her Crown from his ſuccour. <hi>Niſſena</hi> ſhal acknowledge no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to me, ſaid gracious <hi>Fermondo,</hi> ſince the juſtice of her cauſe, and her own merit would have prompted me to greater things then this, to which I am bound as I am a Prince and a Gentleman. If two Gallies will not ſuffice you take four. My care ſhall be to give order for them, and let it be your care to make ſpeedy uſe thereof, leſt ſhee may ſuffer in her intereſt by delay. Bee proſperous in your journey, ſalute her in my name, and intreat her to make uſe of me to the utmoſt of my power. <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all due thanks, and took his leave, thinking ſuddenly to goe from <hi>Rhodes;</hi> though he ſtaid a many days, being detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by tempeſtuous weather. This mean while he was deſired to take <hi>Emerino</hi> for Captain of one of the Gallies, he who was once ſo far in love with <hi>Niſſena;</hi> but his flames of affection being extinguiſhed in the tears of deſperation, he had changed his love affections into the like of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or rather of obſequiouſneſs, deſiring to go to <hi>Cyprus</hi> for no other reaſon, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:121609:75"/>that he might glorie that he had not at all erred in the choice of his love, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathing his heart to a beautie, who deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the government of <hi>Venus</hi> her kingdom. The ſtorms being over, they put from the haven in a ſerene calm, but the ſecond day after their departure, they met with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary winds and foul weather, a calm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing not long after, they might ſee a ſhip not far off, which lying at Anchor, was by the provident Mariners mended in what ſhe had ſuffered by the laſt ſtorms: they turn'd a little out of their way to ſatisfie their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity in knowing to whom ſhe did belong, and from whence ſhe came, and this they did the rather for that they might perhaps, learn from thoſe that were within her ſome tidings of the affairs of <hi>Cyprus:</hi> So as they ſteered their courſe thitherward, and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their Gallie-ſlaves with excellent wines, they incouraged them to row apace: aſſoon as the two Gallies were come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Cannon-ſhot, they were in an unuſual and barbarous manner ſhot at by four piece of Cannon; ſo as inſtead of getting information, they were inforc'd to prepare for fight. <hi>Theocaſtro</hi>'s Gallie received an unluckie ſhot with two bullets beneath the Poop, which giving large entrance unto
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:121609:75"/>the water, made them ſtrike ſail, and ſhip their Oars, to keep out the ſea which frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently ſtole in and was ready to ſwallow up the Gallie. This mean while <hi>Emerino's</hi> Gallie boarded the Enemie, and after a dangerous fight behav'd her ſelf ſo gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as with great ſlaughter of the Enemy, ſhe got a bloudie victorie; there was one Gentleman in the Enemies ſhip, who fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing valliantly, had drawn much bloud from the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> and in a bold and barbarous manner, would never yeild; ſo as they were forced to load him with Irons, and by force to drag him out of the ſhip, whence together with him they took great ſtore of treaſure, and brought it and him into their Gallie, leaving the ſhip without any ſails to the pleaſure of the winds and water: the other rent Gallie being in ſome ſort mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> came in to ſuccour his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion; but met with no other occaſion ſave only to rejoyce with him for his victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: They ſhewed him their bootie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other priſoners, to his great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and aſtoniſhment, he found the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man loaded with Irons to be <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver whom Fortune would have thought ſhe ſhould not have ſufficiently inſulted, had ſhe not after ſo many miſeries brought him
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:121609:76"/>into the hands of his Enemies. <hi>Theocaſtre</hi> was as glad of this deſired Prey, as was <hi>Melaſpus</hi> grieved and almoſt mad to ſee himſelf in his power: whilſt <hi>Emerino</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding who he was, thanked his deſtiny for having delivered up <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s chiefeſt enemy into his power, to whom he thought he could not preſent a more acceptable gift. They forthwith hoiſted their ſails, and gave ſuch way with their Oars as ſhew'd their great deſire to come ſuddenly to ſhore at <hi>Cyprus;</hi> they ſailed ſo ſwiftly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friended by a Weſterly wind, and the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſlaves plying their Oars, as within the ſpace of five hours, they began to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the tops of the promontaries which are in the weſt part of <hi>Cyprus:</hi> nay they did already diſcover the top of high <hi>Olympus,</hi> which being almoſt in the midſt of the Iſland, ſeems to joyn the earth and ſtars together.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Niſſena</hi> was already parted with the two Armies from the parts about <hi>Famagoſta</hi> ſome days ſince, marching towards <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</hi> The Commonwealths horſe led the Van, thoſe of the Crown followed them, and after theſe came ſhe, backt by two Troops of choice Gentlemen, and carried in a chair, having all the Foot for her rear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121609:76"/>
               <hi>Agenor.</hi> and <hi>Filarbo</hi> never parted from her ſide, entertaining her ſometimes with pleaſant, ſomtimes with grave, and ſometimes with ſad diſcourſe. Of which later ſort their communing was when they ſpoke of <hi>Doralbo's</hi> danger, whoſe name though ſhe were glad to hear of, yet was ſhe troubled to think ſome misfortune might have befaln him.</p>
            <p>They made not much haſt in their march, for though Pioners went before them to make the wayes more eaſie for paſſage, they endeavoured to march ſo, as they might doe leaſt prejudice to the Countrey: and the Queen was delighted to be with the Armies, who therfore did not march faſter, or further then ſeated with her conveniency. At laſt they incamped themſelves within 7 miles of <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> and were preparing to make neerer approches with part of the Army, and if it ſhould be thought ſitting to ſtorm the Citie walls, when the 2 Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers who were formerly ſent to enquire after <hi>Doralbo,</hi> and to learn how affairs went in <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> came and deſired that they might be admitted into the Queens preſence, who did not onely give them audience willingly, but when they were brought to her, did with ſome anxiety and impatience ſolicit
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121609:77"/>them to ſay quickly what they had of good or bad to tell her. <hi>It was ſuperfluous</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>that your Majeſty ſhould come atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſuch Forces thither, where you are expected with ſuch devotion by Prince</hi> Doral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo, <hi>by the Nobility, and by all the people, who look for you, we would ſay as for a Goddeſs, did we not think we ſhould offend your modeſty, which will be contented that we ſhall ſay as a Queen by them reverenced and beloved. You are come with an intention of fighting, and your fight is turn'd to triumph.</hi> Here they acquainted her at large with all that had befaln <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who had been in extream danger of loſing his life in revenging her beleeved death: but that being delivered by <hi>Theocaſtro,</hi> he had ſlain the Tyrant; and that afterwards hearing of <hi>Melaſpus</hi> his being fled, he was come out of the Caſtle with the generall applauſe both of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and common people; and that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready had in her name made himſelf abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Maſter of the Citie, on which the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure dominion of all the reſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom did depend. That having heard of her coming by ſome ſtrangers, he was already on his way to come and meet her, and to receive her after ſo many troubles, into the abſolute poſſeſſion of that Crown, which
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:121609:77"/>was due unto her by her ſo many deſerts, and for ſo many other reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Niſſena</hi> was mightily pleaſed with this newes; but the hearing that her beloved <hi>Doralbo</hi> had run hazard of his life, onely in her revenge, cauſed ſo great a paſſion of heart in her, as though it were the effect of joy, had yet ſomewhat mixt with it of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and bitter; paſſions which ſhe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concealed. Having rewarded the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers with a rich chain of Maſſie gold, they were diſmiſt, and ſhe immediatly (her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous-love paſsion ceaſing a little) gave Order that all the Commanders and chief men of the Citie ſhould follow her, for ſhe would goe towards <hi>Niccſia.</hi> The Sun ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted towards the Weſt, to leave the World in darkneſs, and <hi>Doralbo</hi> accompanied with above an hundred Gentlemen, ſpur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d on his Horſe towards that Sunne which brought unto him a riſe of joy, and whoſe bright beams he hoped to enjoy in ſpight of the approaching night. <hi>Niſſena</hi> when ſhe heard a far off the noyſe of Trumpets, which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertis'd her of her Warriers approach, ſhe felt her heart not onely beat, but flutter ſo within her breaſt, as ſhe thought ſhe had been neer death, and that thoſe were the laſt beatings of her ſoul which would open
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:121609:78"/>the paſſage to get out of her body. When <hi>Doralbo</hi> heard from a-far off, the thunder of thoſe Drums which preceded the lightning of that countenance with which his adored <hi>Niſsena</hi> came to aſſault him; he much to his amazement fell a trembling, even then when he found himſelfe more then ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with unquenchable heat. At laſt theſe two ſouls in love, who had long ſince incountred each other in their affections, met one another now with their eyes: Nor did the noyſe of a thouſand musket ſhot, of a hundred Trumpets, and of as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther War Inſtruments, mixt with the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and trampling of horſes, and common ſhouts of joy, hinder them from hearing one another ſay with their looks, and ſtrive who ſhould beſt expreſs themſelves therein; Well met dear eyes ſo long deſired: I now do more then ever feel the fire of love. Thus they ſaid in a language underſtood by none but themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doralbo</hi> leapt from horsback, and had not ſhe hinder'd him, was ready to fall down proſtrate before <hi>Nisſena,</hi> to whom with a trembling voice he ſaid: Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie is at laſt return'd to <hi>Nicoſia</hi> to receive that Crown, which will be proud of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of incircling your Temples: you are
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:121609:78"/>come to receive ſome ſhadow of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which is due to the Immenſitie of your merit. I have not bin wanting for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies in my power, to ſacrifice my life to the Deitie of your greatneſs: but the Gods have pleaſed to preſerve me that upon ſome other occaſion I may be readie to loſe it: I ſhall do it at all times, O my Queen, for your ſervice, for whoſe ſake death would have been and ſhal ever be welcome to me. He would have proceeded, but was thus by her interrupted. Sir, I know how great my obligations are to you; the Crown of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> would be but a weak return of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for what you have done for me. Let it ſuffice I am not ungratefull. <hi>Doralbo</hi> would have reply'd, but ſtruck through with a pleaſing ſmile and affable look from her, his anſwer was turnd into a ſigh, which though it were cut ſhort off, made the inamour'd Queen fully underſtand that ſhe was the Shrine that he adored. She afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd her ſelfe to receive obſequious appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations from the other Gentlemen, who with reverence bowed unto her, to whom ſhe anſwered with ſuch a Majeſtical Grace, as all of them blamed Fortune, which had ſo long kept her from that ſublime degree which her ſo many perefctions did deſerve.
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:121609:79"/>All the Ladies of <hi>Nicofia</hi> came to her clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in black, as a Livery which they wore to the memory of the deceaſed King, and to their Queens Widowhood, to whom humbly bowing themſelves, they found in her an affable but not abject correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency; ſuch as ſhewed Majeſty, but not pride: whence that reverentiall love began in them, with which <hi>Niſſena</hi> was ever after reſpected and beloved by all her Subjects of whatſoever condition. Before they could get to <hi>Nicoſia,</hi> darkneſs had canopied over the vvhole Orizon, ſo as the great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of lighted Torches and Bonſires did in an inſtant ſo inlighten the darkneſs of the night, as it had no reaſon to envie the brighteſt day; and yet all theſe flames and heats appear'd to <hi>Doralbo</hi> but obſcure hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in reſpect of thoſe beams which darted from <hi>Niſsena's</hi> eyes. She came unto the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace amidſt the noyſe of Warl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; the ſhouts and acclamations of the rejoycing people; and calling to mind how ſhe had not long before fled from thence abandoned by all, and how ſhe now retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned reverenced and cried up, nay as it were, adored, ſhe could not but admire the ſtrauge fickleneſs of Fortune.</p>
            <p>She would not forbear giving of audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:121609:79"/>and receiving congratulations from the numerous inundation of Ladies, Lords, Tituladoes, and perſonages of all conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, til ſhe was inſufferably weary; but at laſt ſhe was inforc'd to betake her ſelf to her reſt. She gave order that <hi>Eurania, Doralbo, Agenor</hi> of <hi>Soria</hi> and <hi>Filarbo</hi> ſhould ſup in privat with her: the chief Commanders of the Army having their Lodgings appointed out to them in the Court, and being treated with ſuch ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſitie as belonged unto them. The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were entertained in the field with ſuch abundance of rich Wines, of vvhich <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus</hi> is very plentiful, &amp; with ſuch varietie of Viands, as the Soldiers ſpent the whole night almoſt in their cups and eating. The Queen vvas readie to ſit dovvn vvith the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at the Table vvhen ſhe vvas inform'd that tvvo Gentlemen of <hi>Rhodes</hi> deſired au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: bring them in, ſaid ſhe, I ſhal ſoon diſpatch them <hi>Theocaſtro</hi> and <hi>Emerino</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred together with the miſerable <hi>Melaſpus</hi> loaded with Irons, who proſtrating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before her, preſented <hi>Melaſpus</hi> to her as a ſlave. All were amazed at this ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected a ſight; but <hi>Doralbo,</hi> I know not whether out of diſdain or pittie, a colour coming into his face, broke forth into
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:121609:80"/>theſe words: The Heavens at laſt leave no guilty perſons unpuniſhed. Who would ever have imagined moſt gratious Queen, that this fellow ſhould at this time be brought hither in this condition, perfectly to compleat your Majeſties happineſs and ſafety? Theſe, ſaid ſhe, are miracles which divine Juſtice knows only how to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: Let him be led unto the Caſtle, and let him be well treated there, I bequeath him to you Prince <hi>Doralbo;</hi> appointing you to be his Judge; but upon this condition, that you abſolve him of being partaker of his fathers wickedneſs. Go and be of good comfort <hi>Melaſpus,</hi> ſaid <hi>Doralbo,</hi> you have already begun to taſte of the Queens cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie. <hi>Theocaſtre</hi> and <hi>Emerino,</hi> having recounted their adventures, ſate down like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at the Table with <hi>Niſſena,</hi> who had leaſure enough at a long and gladſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to let <hi>Doralbo</hi> know by her moſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt favours, that ſhe lov'd him better then her ſelf.</p>
            <p>Four whole days were paſt over by theſe two Lovers, neither of them daring to diſcover their affections, unleſs by their looks, and by letting ſome little words e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape which equivocally noted their inward heat of heart; in which <hi>Niſſena</hi> buſied
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:121609:80"/>her ſelf onely in diſpenſing her rewards and favours, and in winning not only the love, but the Idolatry of her Subjects. <hi>Niſſena</hi> thought it unbefitting her to ſpeak her love to <hi>Doralbo,</hi> and though ſhe knew ſhe was in regard of her prioritie bound to begin firſt in the declaration thereof, and was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reſolved to do ſo, her innate modeſtie would not ſuffer her ſo to do, or elſe her ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry affection hindred her: it being impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for one who truely loves, to ſay he loves. <hi>Doralbo</hi> who did not believe he merited <hi>Niſſena</hi>'s ſervice, much leſs her love, would rather have choſen to die, then to make his affection known unto her by diſcovery of his flames: Who am I, (ſaid he within himſelf) or what am I, that I ſhould pretend love unto ſo beautifull a Queen? 'Tis true, I am born a Prince: I have ſerved her to the evident neglect of my life, and I love her more dearly then mine own ſoul. But what's all this? She merits greater things: Should I diſcover my love, and ſhe not correſpond with me therein, what would become of me? is it not ſafer to ſay nothing, to ſerve, obſerve, and nouriſh ſtil my hopes, then to receive my death from her ſcorn, or from her flat denial? if ſhe be pleaſed to Crown our
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:121609:81"/>love with reward, ſhe will not want ways and means how to do it. Thus did both ſhe and he in vain lament; which crafty <hi>Eurania</hi> perceiving, and compaſſionating their too abſtenious ravings, ſhe invited them one day after dinner into a Cloſſet to ſee certain Pictures, wherein were drawn to the life the affections between <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis,</hi> and hence ſhe took an occaſion free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſay unto them; this is the way of love my Children; I know <hi>Niſſena</hi> and <hi>Doral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo,</hi> that you burn in love each with other in unquenchable fires, and ſtrive who ſhould love one another beſt; why do you then thus id'ly conſume your ſelves away, cold in the midſt of flames? Say <hi>Nisſena,</hi> I take thee <hi>Doralbo</hi> for my husband. Say you <hi>Doralbo,</hi> I take thee <hi>Nisſena</hi> for my wife: ſo ſo, imbrace each other; Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial love is no ſhame to the world, nor fault committed againſt heaven. The two Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, with a bluſhing countenance and ill aſſured look, confirm'd her ſayings, and grew ſo bold, as at one and the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant they ran ſo greedily to interchange a kiſs, as their ſouls had almoſt flown through exceſs of joy from out their ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd breaſts.</p>
            <pb n="159" facs="tcp:121609:81"/>
            <p>Here ended the ſorrws, and began the joys of <hi>Nisſena</hi> and <hi>Doralbo,</hi> who reigned proſperouſly, and loved each other faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully all their life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
